<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Praxis catholica, or, The countryman's universal remedy wherein is plainly and briefly laid down the nature, matter, manner, place and cure of most diseases, incident to the body of man, not hitherto discovered, whereby any one of an ordinary capacity may apprehend the true cause of his distempers, wherein his cure consists, and the means to effect it : together with rules how to order children in that most violent disease of vomiting and looseness, &amp;c. : useful likewise for seamen and travellers : also an account of an imcomparable powder for wounds or hurts which cure any ordinary ones at once dressing / written by Robert Couch ... ; now published with divers useful additions (for publick benefit) by Chr. Pack ...</title>
            <author>Couch, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9840</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12713829</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12713829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66140</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34728)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 684:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Praxis catholica, or, The countryman's universal remedy wherein is plainly and briefly laid down the nature, matter, manner, place and cure of most diseases, incident to the body of man, not hitherto discovered, whereby any one of an ordinary capacity may apprehend the true cause of his distempers, wherein his cure consists, and the means to effect it : together with rules how to order children in that most violent disease of vomiting and looseness, &amp;c. : useful likewise for seamen and travellers : also an account of an imcomparable powder for wounds or hurts which cure any ordinary ones at once dressing / written by Robert Couch ... ; now published with divers useful additions (for publick benefit) by Chr. Pack ...</title>
                  <author>Couch, Robert.</author>
                  <author>Packe, Christopher, fl. 1670-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48], 165, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Hartford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Magic, mystic, and spagiric --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Praxis Catholica:</hi> OR, THE COUNTRYMAN'S Univerſal Remedy: WHEREIN plainly and briefly laid down the Nature, Matter, Manner, Place and Cure of moſt <hi>DISEASES,</hi> Incident to the Body of Man; Not hitherto diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Whereby any one of an ordinary Capacity may apprehend the true Cauſe of his Diſtempers, wherein his Cure conſiſts, and the Means to effect it; together with Rules how to order Children in that moſt violent Diſeaſe of vomiting and Looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> uſeful likewiſe for Seamen and Travellers.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſo an Account of an Incomparable Powder for Wounds or Hurts which cure any ordinary ones at once dreſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritten by <hi>Robert Couch,</hi> ſometimes Practitioner in Phyſick and Chyrurgery, at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow publiſhed with divers uſeful Additions (for publick benefit) by <hi>Chr. Pack,</hi> Operator in Chymiſtry.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enim ſi dare vitam proprius Dei munus eſt, certe datam tueri, jam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fugientem retineri, Deo proximum fatea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur oportet. <bibl>
                  <hi>Eraſm.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>don,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS Highly Honoured AND MUCH Eſteemed FRIEND, COLONEL <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>RANCIS WILLIS,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Little <hi>TRACT</hi> humbly offers and ſubmits it ſelf.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SEing it hath been your generous Care, and Love to your Native Country, to
<pb facs="tcp:66140:3"/>
tranſplant this <hi>Exotick</hi> from <hi>Tranſmarine</hi> Parts to us; I think it highly reaſonable that you ſhould have the Overſight of its <hi>Culture</hi> and <hi>Growth:</hi> That as it hath here received its <hi>Firſt Being</hi> from your <hi>Charity</hi> to the <hi>Publick,</hi> it may alſo under your <hi>Name</hi> continue to grow and increaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> your <hi>Knowledge</hi> in true <hi>Medicine,</hi> and intimate <hi>Acquaintance</hi> you had with Mr. <hi>Couch</hi> the <hi>Author,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:66140:3"/>
hath rendred you as able to Judge, as fit to Patronize. His Judgments of Diſeaſes are ſound and accurate, and deduced from ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as Heathens and their Followers never yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, or were able to refute; as for the Medicines be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes, you know, Sir, they are not Toys or Trifles to gull an unwary World, but ſuch whoſe virtues and power of healing are undeniable, both from what they have done,
<pb facs="tcp:66140:4"/>
and are always ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. What I have added is only a farther Confirmation of Matter of Fact, the which with the whole I humbly preſent to you as it is (except Errours, if any, which I reſerve to my ſelf) deſiring your Favourable Acceptance of thoſe ſmall Endeavours of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant, CHR. PACK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Once having the Fortune to ſee this Little Book of Mr. <hi>Couch</hi>'s in the hand of a Gentleman living in <hi>Carolina</hi> (who did me the favour to lend it me to peruſe) I was ſo pleaſed with his Sentiments of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and manner of deſcribing them, that I heartily wiſhed it were here made Publick; but the Gentleman's ſuddain depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of <hi>England</hi> recalled the Book out of my hands before I
<pb facs="tcp:66140:5"/>
could half tranſcribe it. Not withſtanding at length I attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my deſire through the Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of the Worthy Colonel <hi>Francis Willis</hi> (a Candid Lover and Promoter of true Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine) who procured me this Book in Manuſcript from <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia</hi> (where Mr. <hi>Couch</hi> died) from whom alſo I had long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received the Knowledge of thoſe moſt Excellent Remedies uſed by Mr. <hi>Couch</hi> for curing the Diſtempers treated of in this Book. But ſeeing that all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines now adays (of which there are too many) publiſhed as <hi>Arcanums,</hi> and bearing the names of Univerſal Remedies, come ſo far ſhort of their ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:66140:5"/>
pretences, they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed only Engines employed for gain, that I could not reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably expect that thoſe Worthy Medicaments ſhould be beheld with any other Aſpect, if the curing of Diſeaſes ſhould be here reſtrained to them only. Wherefore I have here added o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Medicines for the cure of each Diſeaſe, &amp; ſuch as are good and effectual, in which I have candidly dealt with all perſons, and left every one to his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty what to uſe. Moreover be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many Perſons (into whoſe hands this Book may come) who live remote in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, upon ſuddain occaſion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have time enough to ſend
<pb facs="tcp:66140:6"/>
to me for the Powder and Pill, I have alſo directed the uſe of ſuch as they may be ſerved withal nearer home, by which I hope I may juſtly avoid the cenſure of publiſhing this Book ſolely for my own advantage. Truly I abhor ſuch private ends which are not to be attained without hypocriſie, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices and ruines of Lives and Families: but ſo faſt are moſt people tied to the Heathens precepts of healing, and to the modes and faſhions of times and perſons, that they know not truth when they meet her, but obſtinately perſiſt in errour (for its age ſake) and ſo voluntarily come ſhort of the benefits of
<pb facs="tcp:66140:6"/>
Gods healing mercies, falling ſhort of true knowledge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they think themſelves to be already ſufficiently inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, according to the ſaying of <hi>Seneca, Multi ad virtatem perveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re potuiſſent niſi ſe putaſſent perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſe:</hi> So that it may be as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed in relation as well to the body as the ſoul, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny periſh through unbelief: neither will it be otherwiſe till the time cometh when the groans of the Creation to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from this vanity ſhall ceaſe, and the <hi>Elias</hi> of Arts ſhall appear to reſtore all things.</p>
            <p>This little Treatiſe may be uſeful for every conſiderate Reader, enabling him in divers
<pb facs="tcp:66140:7"/>
Maladies to get help at a cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more certain rate than uſual. Neither will it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome to the <hi>Tyro's</hi> in the <hi>Helmontian</hi> Philoſophy, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine whom it may accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date in many caſes; others no doubt at firſt ſight will not free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive it, becauſe (to them) the Doctrine may be altogether novel, but if they will rightly weigh the diſcourſes of Diſeaſes and compare them with the common precepts and notions of healing (out of deſire to find out the truth) they ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly apprehend them to be more agreeable to the frame and ſimplicity of nature than the other. But as for ſuch Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers
<pb facs="tcp:66140:7"/>
to Heatheniſm, as have taken a Leafe of their Opinions for life, I do not queſtion but to them it will be diſguſtful, they will contend about the ſhell till they loſe the Kernel, but be it as it will, I deſign nothing but well in it, what I have ſaid being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of love to truth, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon any man's perſon or intereſt. To conclude, I ſhall ſtill make it my buſineſs to looſe the bonds of Animals, Vegita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Minerals; endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with Chimical Keys to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock the choyceſt. Cabinets of Nature, and whatever I from time to time (by the Divine Bounty) ſhall be able to take from thence, ſhall readily be
<pb facs="tcp:66140:8"/>
communicated to the uſe of the ſick; more eſpecially into the hands of honeſt and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Artiſts, who may uſe them to the honour of God the giver, their own credit, and the relief of many a miſerable perſon. In the mean time I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ſervant in the fire,</hi> Chr. Pack.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Laboratory, at the Sign of the</hi> Globe <hi>and</hi> Chymical Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces <hi>in the</hi> Poſtern <hi>near</hi> Moor-gate.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:8"/>
            <head>To all Ingenious Students and Practitioners in Phyſick and Chyrurgery.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Brethren:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE read of Renowned Dr. <hi>Harvey</hi> our Countryman, who tells us he opened an Impoſthume in a Gentleman's left ſide, where he beheld the <hi>Dyaſtole</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtole</hi> of the heart, and he touched it, and found it inſenſible, though it gives life unto every part.</p>
            <p>'Tis an Argument he is of eminent and publick conducement, uſeful to derive good to others, who it leaſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of private Injuries offered himſelf. As for Injuries I have had a double ſhare, and I have not only forgiven them, but forgotten them; I ſhould gladly do them good that did me hurt.</p>
            <p>There is a ſaving in <hi>Germany,</hi> poor <hi>Luther</hi> made many a Rich man; I
<pb facs="tcp:66140:9"/>
could be contented to be poor, ſo I might be inſtrumental to enrich Artiſts in the Knowledge of Healing, whereby it might tend to the peoples greater good, and God's greater Glory.</p>
            <p>The Laws of Charity oblige a man that hath gone in a dangerous way to preadmoniſh him that intends the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Satis Eloquentiae: Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae parum: abunde fabularum audivintus.</note>So that I ſtand bound to adviſe you that you conſult not ſo much with that learned Theory of the Schools; which is good for nothing but to diſpute and contend.</p>
            <p>Learned Dr. <hi>Charlton</hi> in the end of his Epiſtle to his Tranſlation of <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> upon the Magnetick Cure of Wounds. I remember hath a ſaying to this effect: There are many things (faith be) that have been diſputed in the Schools and Colledges, that have been received for truths among them; and they have ſeemed to have Reaſon for their Foundation, and Learning for
<pb facs="tcp:66140:9"/>
their Defence or Walls: but when they have come to be experienced, they have fallen to the ground, and nothing of truth hath appeared in them <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They can inform you nothing of truth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the knowledge of a Diſeaſe; nor a good method in curing, nor a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Medicine to effect a Cure.</p>
            <p>Practice is the beſt part of Phyſick, Obſervation the ſureſt, and the Theory of the Ancients, the uncertaineſt and emptieſt. This we are taught by the example of many Eminent Phyſicians both Chymical and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenical;<note n="*" place="margin">Paracelſus, Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Crollius.</note> who could with their <hi>Arcanum</hi>'s cure thoſe Diſeaſes that were termed <hi>opprobria Medicorum:</hi> And we ſee likewiſe thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Riverius, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtus, Johnſtonus,</hi> and many more Modern Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Phyſicians that were trained up in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Schooles; yet when they were to encounter any ſtubborn Diſeaſe, they would not truſt to their Weapons, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:66140:10"/>
often been foiled with them) but ran to their <hi>Arcanum</hi>'s, as their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations witneſs.</p>
            <p>Not that I think all their Secrets were Chymical Preparations; for I have abundance of reaſon to believe that there are ſingular ſpecifical virtues in Senſitive and Vegitive Simples, and of a far greater power than ſome of our large Compoſitions.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo credulous, as to believe all to be true that the Chymiſts boaſt of, neither am I ſo diffident, as to think all the Schools have treated of to be falſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Comede da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctylos &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jice foras du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritiem.</note> Read them as our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Divines read the Schoolmen.</p>
            <p>Let not any one think <hi>(qui forſan Latinè, aut Graecè intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere poteſt)</hi> that becauſe he is a good Scholar, he can preſently be a good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician: if he doth,<note place="margin">Non quaerit aeger Medicum elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentem, ſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem, <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </note> be ſure he will be miſtaken; for he will find the Art of healing to conſiſt in
<pb facs="tcp:66140:10"/>
another kind of Learning. <hi>Novi nuper quendam,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Primroſe, qui cum ſe Medicum profiteretur; quamvis leviſſimè eâ diſciplinâ tinctus foret; talis tamen habitus eſt ob quandam Latinae Linguae cognitionem:</hi> but there is a great difference betwixt ſuch men and ſound Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;<note place="margin">Garruloſum Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum alterum morbum aegro eſſe.</note> 'tis one thing to give a Patient a long and learned diſcourſe of his Diſeaſe; but it's another thing to give him a preſent remedy.</p>
            <p>I have but only hinted at Diſeaſes, (becauſe I intended this but for an <hi>Enchyridion</hi>) yet you may perceive by it, that we have been blinded in the true knowledge of the Cauſes, Places, and Cures of Diſeaſes; I muſt confeſs I owe much of it unto<note n="*" place="margin">Vir magno judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, &amp; praeſtante doctrina, clariſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> 
               <hi>Helmont,</hi> the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard-bearer of Phyſick; yet I ſpeak not his Judgment, but mine own, having enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a belief from experience; I have
<pb facs="tcp:66140:11"/>
not written any thing in this Tract, but what I am perſwaded of the truth of, though it may in moſt places ſeem (to ſome) at the firſt view to be Paradoxes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet upon a more accurate inſpection i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may become received Truths. And if this crude labour of mine finds accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance with young Practitioners; I ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpend ſome time to enlarge upon it to their ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>As for my <hi>Arcanums</hi> you'l all conclude, it is not fit to put them to publick view: if any of you ſhould deſire the knowledge of them, <hi>malè docuit.</hi> And to caſt them at the feet of all Pretenders to Phyſick, they may be abuſed by their ignorance i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the preparing, doſe, time or manner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for one may have as good Medicine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for a Diſeaſe as can be by the Art of ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> invented,<note place="margin">Morborum reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, ſi ab indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis uſurpentur venena, ſi vero à doctis &amp; exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis deorum auxilia ſunt.</note> yet if he know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not the time when, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the form in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor the doſe how much; he may inſtead of curing kill the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent:
<pb facs="tcp:66140:11"/>
Beſides, there are ſome idle and careleſs Artiſts, who may not deſerve it, that never inquire into Diſeaſes, nor yet Medicine; but expect every thing to be popt into their mouths:<note place="margin">Dii laboribus, omnia vendunt.</note> the Gods ſold all by ſweats; night unto night ſheweth knowledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the gift of healing is a great gift, which comes from above, from which you are to fetch the knowledge of Medicine: And I doubt whether it be ſafe to divulge Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets: we have no ſuch precedent from any Author: we ſee <hi>Riverius</hi> in all the four Centuries of his obſervations; there was hardly a Diſeaſe but he cured with his <hi>Febrifugium</hi> and <hi>Calomanenas,</hi> and who knows what they were; (I have a very ſtrong faith, that my Powder which I call my <hi>Arcanum Univerſale,</hi> was his <hi>Febrifugium,</hi> for the doſe and operation is alike; and if mine were not the ſame I am confident it is not inferiour to it, nor any extant) they bid us ſeek and we may find; for they have
<pb facs="tcp:66140:12"/>
told us nothing, but a Story, how <hi>Actae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was Metamorphos'd for preſenting <hi>Diana</hi> naked to the People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All their Secrets died with them; or at leaſt communicated to ſuch Friends as kept them from a publick view; then let us do as they did, and we may attain unto that they had; we muſt not content our ſelves in the knowledge of a little <hi>Mithridate</hi> or <hi>Diaſcordium;</hi> or to give a Purge or a Clyſter; but let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day repent us of yeſterdays Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>Let us drive to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,<note n="*" place="margin">Ars longa, vita brevis, experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia difficilis, &amp;c.</note> though the Age of a man is too ſhort to obtain it: It is much againſt my temper, to conceal any thing from any Ingenious and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Artiſt; but I have been much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and I am ſorry to ſpeak it; that if I had told leſs, it would have been more for my credit and profit: I can ſay with the Poet <hi>Ovid:</hi>
               <q>Hos ego verſiculos feci tulit alter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores.</q>
               <pb facs="tcp:66140:12"/>
Nevertheleſs, the unworthineſs of ſome, ſhall not detract from the worth of any Civil and Ingenious Brother: I ſhall always be civil to all, but eſpecially to thoſe that I find are ſo:<note place="margin">Ars praeclariſſima Artifex ſordiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> I am ſorry to ſee ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhabby and courſe ſpirited Fellows, that practiſe in ſo high and honourable a Calling: There is ſuch a vaſt diſproportion between the Art and the Artiſt; that well may the Art be aſhamed to own them: There are not only ignorant Jack-daws that are intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders upon this worthy Art, which ſquare out all things by their crooked and indirect Rules; but likewiſe there are <hi>Pompeys</hi> and <hi>Caeſars</hi> too, who ſcorn to admit of Equals, and be <hi>Caeſars</hi> or no bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who think it much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Greatneſs to adviſe with any. If they are at any time petitioned unto it, they grant it with this reſervation to themſelves, to deny every thing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay, though it be never ſo undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and clear a truth; they would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:66140:13"/>
twenty ſhould die under their hands, than part with one to be cured by another, that's a great affront to their Ambition whereunto they ſacrifice ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a mans life, and diſſemble their Pride under the cloak of Humility, and ſo blind the poor Country-man; that they think ſuch a one to be <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that his Medicines were extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the balm of <hi>Gilead;</hi> when he may be but ſome Impoſter; and his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, it may be, no better than a little Cow-dung, or ſome thing worſe; and as the Papiſts are kept in blindneſs, by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Language they underſtand not, to the hazard of their ſouls; ſo are many amongſt us led away (by ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers) in harkning unto the falſe Doctrine of the Heathens, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of our bodies: for they thunder out Art in <hi>Quarto,</hi> and Conſcience in <hi>Folio,</hi> and ſhower down ſuch Heavenly Apologies for their deceit and ignorance, with ſuch claſhes of Lightning, that frights the ſimple into ſuch a belief, as
<pb facs="tcp:66140:13"/>
to miſtruſt, were a crime unpardonable; whereby they are canoniz'd on Earth, and written in the Rubrick, in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar of the World. I believe there have been many ſuch Saints on Earth, that never found any room in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Brethren; have a care none of you be ever found akin to any ſuch Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide; though you may with ſuch jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles and indirect means deceive the people, you cannot deceive the all-ſeeing God; he will make you ſmart for it in the end, when the popular applauſe of the World ſhall but torment you the more. The life of man is more worth than all the Creation: And as it is pretious to the Creature; ſo it is to the Creator; and he will not ſuffer it to be trampled upon (by the pride of any) without revenge; and yet thoſe ſad fellows may be much cried up and in great eſteem amongſt the vulgar, when a far more knowing and worthy Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner may not be regarded. Let not this be any diſcouragement to any young
<pb facs="tcp:66140:14"/>
Practitioner; for if there be anything of worth in him, and he acts like an Artiſt, let him expect to be undervalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ignorant, and let him not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire why it is ſo; for we find that it hath been the unhappineſs of all Ages, that Falſhood hath been preferred before Truth, and perſons of no worth or value, have had the precedency of perſons of true worth and eſteem:<note place="margin">Scientia non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet inimicum praeter ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> as for the vulgar, whom Nature huddl'd up in haſt; that Act meerly by the prerogative of depraved Nature, ſpeak againſt every thing but what is naught; whatſoever is of Worth and Art, be ſure they will diſlike; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt all Perſons, but ſuch as comply with their ignorance, whoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Fury is like the Waves of the Sea, driven by the fury of enraged <hi>Boreas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have read of <hi>Cato</hi> that he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four times brought (by the vulgar ſort of people) to the Judgment-Seat,
<pb facs="tcp:66140:14"/>
and every time came off acquitted; what a great happineſs it is, when a man hath many malicious Enemies, to find impartial and upright Judges.</p>
            <p>Every Country hath its <hi>Diana,</hi> as well as <hi>Epheſus:</hi> And he that will not ſacrifice with the people, ſhall be crucified by them; but he that doth keep a pure and undefiled Conſcience towards God, and acts like an honeſt and ingenious Artiſt towards his Neighbour may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a Cordial from the World's poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and live above the reach of Envy.</p>
            <p>The moſt ſplendent Creature is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time clouded, and the moſt vertuous Lady ſuffers an Eclipſe in her innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy by ſome malevolent Neighbour when a Strumpet goes unſuſpected.</p>
            <p>It is not every Artiſt's fortune to arrive at <hi>Corinth;</hi> but I could wiſh every ingenious Artiſt could practice what he knows, and that he knew more, to practiſe better: ſo I deſire to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, when I ſay that Practiſe is the beſt part of Phyſick; that there
<pb facs="tcp:66140:15"/>
muſt be firſt a knowledge of the Diſeaſe, and likewiſe of the Remedy, and ſo to proportion the Remedy to the Diſeaſe; and not to try practices on mens bodies;<note n="*" place="margin">Care at ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus opto, Quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ab eventu facta notanda pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</note> that the Poet curſed; but firſt you muſt know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you practiſe, and ſo your practice will confirm your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: So I conclude with this advice; firſt, let God go before you, to counſel and direct you unto the direct means; let him go with you to crown it with a good Succeſs, and let him follow you, to take all the glory unto whom all glory is due.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caepta faveat Deus, ac vota noſtra ſecundet.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So wiſheth, <hi>Robert Couch.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:15"/>
            <head>TO MY Candid and Cordial COUNTRYMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends and Countreymen:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce Death and Diſeaſes (which are Diametrically oppoſite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life) are entailed unto us through the Tranſgreſſion of our firſt Parents, the Creator and ſole Authour of life, foreſeeing the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Natures, to withſtand the ſtrength of ſuch mortal Enemies, created Medicine from the beginning out of the Earth, to correct the fury and tyranny of Diſeaſes (whereof Death is the Daughter) whereby each ſhould be at his good pleaſure; and ſo governs it at his will, that he
<pb facs="tcp:66140:16"/>
permits and ſuffers this man to die, and that to be ſick by ſecondary Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which happen as well directly as irregularly,</p>
            <p>And whereas the Nature of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes are various; ſo he hath endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Earth with various and ſundry Medicinal Vertues; and he hath likewiſe called and ordained ſome to adminiſter and apply ſuch ſuitable and fit means, as the nature of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes do require. But the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties by reaſon of the inviſibility of the Diſeaſe, and the great obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the knowledge of Medicine have fruſtrated many in their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. All Arts and Sciences (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Phyſick) have grown to ſome pitch; but that hath rather gone backward, till within ſome late years, famous <hi>Helmont</hi> (to whom the Art it ſelf ſtands much obliged) and ſome Renowned Phyſicians of our Native Countrey, have begun to caſt off that black vail of deceit with
<pb facs="tcp:66140:16"/>
which it was cloathed by the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rems of the Heathens.</p>
            <p>Indeed the gate of healing hath remained ſhut from the Cradle of the World; and the Schooles of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> inſtead of opening it ſhut it cloſer, and made it more myſterious than ever was intended by the firſt Creator.</p>
            <p>The natures, cauſes and places of Diſeaſes were not rightly underſtood by them, whereby they failed in their Remedies; they had ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard unto the effects, that they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the cauſes, which pernicious and deſtructive courſe is practiſed ſtill, by ſuch who are wholly led by their Rules.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the whole intent of this ſmall Tract is to undeceive you, that you be not deceived of your lives by ſuch erroneous preſervers, and that you give not your money for what's not bread, nor buy a Snake inſtead of an Eele. I know it is not
<pb facs="tcp:66140:17"/>
Artiſt-like to build ſo great a Porch to ſo ſmall a Fabrick: but if it tend to the Owners more conveniency, it is to be diſpenſed withall. Indulge me therefore Reader, to give thee ſome cautions; (it may be for thy Good) Firſt, touching the Diſeaſe: Secondly, touching the Phyſician. Inaſmuch as we were poyſoned from the Tree of Knowledge; ſo no other Tree could we fetch an Antidote from; but the Tree of Life, which was for healing of the Nations: So Diſeaſes are only cured by fit and ſuitable means; for thou mayſt be kill'd by a bad means as well as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored by a good. Wherefore be an earneſt Suiter to Heaven, that thou mayſt have the right means from Earth, and a benediction with it, which will make it operate the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>And as it muſt be a true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per means that muſt cure thy Diſeaſe, ſo have a ſpecial care the Remedy
<pb facs="tcp:66140:17"/>
come not too late. How many have been robbed of their lives upon that ſcore? Opportunity is the ſoul and perfection of Phyſick, you may loſe that opportunity to day,<note place="margin">Poſt eſt occaſio calva.</note> that the price of the World cannot procure thee to morrow: take time by the fore top leſt it be bald be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</p>
            <p>There are two great Obſtacles which commonly make many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantages; the firſt is, from the perſwaſion of Friends; the ſecond, from the flattery of Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when any one is taken ſick, one Friend adviſeth him to ſuch a thing, another perſwades another, and a third another; telling him if it does him no good it will do him no hurt: But there is no ſuch <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> will ſtand; for if it do not exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate the Diſeaſe; yet it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard the Cure; and ſo by trying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain means, you looſe the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb facs="tcp:66140:18"/>
of a ſure Remedy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Deceit and Flattery of the Diſeaſe; when Diſeaſes aſſault you very ſtrongly in the<note n="*" place="margin">Quanmvis non nunquam morbi in eorum princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piis abſque peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo tibi videntur: vires &amp; in mores tamen ſenſim de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jicientur &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rampentur ut po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtea nulla ſalutis ſpes ſuper fit, at morbus qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo curabiis fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, malignitam neglecta incurabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> beginning, they may have ſuch Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals and Reſpites, that you apprehend your ſelves better to day than you was yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and that while the Diſeaſe doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly: undermine your lives, and then aſſaults with greater fury than he did at firſt.</p>
            <p>Others are very mild and gentle in the beginning, yet they may be very malign: <hi>parvae febres quando qui valde malignae;</hi> whereby you do not ſo much miſtruſt them, much leſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their danger.</p>
            <p>And ſometimes thoſe that labour under ſharp Diſeaſes, the Symptoms
<pb facs="tcp:66140:18"/>
have been ſo remiſs and dark, that it hath been a very difficult thing for an able Phyſician to preſage either life or death, and when he hath paſſed his Judgment, within few hours there hath been ſuch a change, that he hath been fool'd in his Prognoſtick.</p>
            <p>In others again, Diſeaſes have layen ſo hid and obſcure, that they have died before they were percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be ſick, of which we have had many ſad Examples, of ſome that have died ſuddenly, who have carried thoſe Diſeaſes undiſcovered about them, that wanted nothing but the word, immediately to run them to the heart.</p>
            <p>Now I have ſhewed you the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and Flattery of Diſeaſes, which have couzened thouſands of their lives; of whom you will do well to learn to beware, and act prudently, to prevent by miſtruſt, what you would not have come ſuddenly and unexpected.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:66140:19"/>And as I have told you the deceit of Diſeaſes, ſo I ſhall tell you the deceit of Phyſicians; I mean ſuch who have built more upon the ſandy Foundation of the<note n="*" place="margin">As if it were for their ſake God created Medicine, and Chriſtians ſhould be beholden to them for it.</note> Pagans and Heathens then upon a ſure and rocky Foundation, who have ſtudie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more to get money than to cure their Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>It hath pitied me many a time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſee that Old Saying too often verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saepe plus mali à Medico quam à Morbo.</note> That many times there is more danger from the Phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſician, than from the Diſeaſe, ſuch a Phyſician as practi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth by Old Authors. And that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may the better know them, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſome of their juggles, I ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> recite ſome of their Practiſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when ſuch a Deceiver is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto a Patient, if his Diſeaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be grown to a great height
<pb facs="tcp:66140:19"/>
which hath made him dangerouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill: (which was the end God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Phyſick and Phyſicians for, to relieve ſuch diſtreſſed Natures) he ſtands at a diſtance, fearing to come near (like a low ſpirited fellow) leſt he receive ſuch a kick from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe in his rotten reputation, as he may not eaſily recover: but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves rather to hazard the loſs of a poor Patient, then venture the loſs of his ſmall credit; wherefore he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to look on, and ſee which will get the Victory: in the mean while he excuſes his juggle, telling, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe is not yet come to an height; and by ſuch a time he hopes to find a <hi>Criſis,</hi> and then he may ſafely take ſomething, in the interim adviſeth an Ale-brew, or Herb-Candle, many more ſuch juggles they have to ſend people to their Graves: Juſt as if your houſe were on fire, And one comes and counſels you to let it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone till it burn to the top of the
<pb facs="tcp:66140:20"/>
Houſe, and then is the ſureſt quenching it, you take his counſel. Now 'tis poſſible that the Heavens may pour down ſuch a ſhower of rain as may extinguiſh it; but whether they do or not, doth not this man well adviſe you, think you; or as if an Enemy hath entered a Garriſon, it is not ſafe to reſiſt him, till he come to the heart of the Town: But good Souldiers will tell you otherwiſe, that what their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my gets they ſhall get it by Inches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>Criſis</hi> they ſo much talk of, is nothing but an effect of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Helmont</hi> hath well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> Nature hath oppoſite Virtues and Faculties, which hold a great harmony with the Moon's Motion, whereby there is, it may be, ſome ſmall change a little while through her Motions; but they are not cauſed by the Moon, but by Nature harmoning
<pb facs="tcp:66140:20"/>
with her Motion: But what of this? what is it to the taking away thy Diſeaſe? indeed it may help a little a bad Medicine, but a good Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine will make a Laudable <hi>Criſis,</hi> let the Moon be where ſhe will; in ſtaying thus for the Moon, many have loſt the Sun.</p>
            <p>Now this Deceiver finding Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to have caſt the Diſeaſe, runs in and congratulates her Victory with a dram of his Bottle; and inſtead of helping her up, many times keeps her the longer down: But if the Diſeaſe hath caſt Nature, then he gives his Relation this Cordial: That all the men in the World could do no more, and that he did conſult with forty Learned Authors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if this will not operate then he gives them this<note n="*" place="margin">A Medicine to cauſe Rest or Sleep.</note> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate in a dram of <hi>Aqua Coeleſtis, viz.</hi> It was the will of God it ſhould be ſo, and that his time was come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:66140:21"/>
ſo his decets are buried with his poor Patient: But how doth he make you believe it was the will of God, and that his time was come? we all know, God doth permit that which he doth not will: God may permit this Impoſtor to give a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive means, or not to uſe the right; for it is almoſt all one: If thou haſt not ſomething to take off the poyſon of the Diſeaſe, the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Diſeaſe will take off thee.</p>
            <p>In vain had the Creatour created Medicines out of the Earth from the beginning, unleſs the natural terms and bounds of things might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed by healing and Medicines: And likewiſe the Tree of Life had been in vain in Paradiſe; if he that hath bounded the life of man had not together by the ſame endeavour appointed all means requiſite for the bounds of life: then, if I uſe no means, or not the right means, my
<pb facs="tcp:66140:21"/>
bound is ſet, which I ſhall not paſs over, according to that ſaying; woe is me that my Pilgrimage is prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; thy Youth ſhall be renewed like the Eagle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's a ſecond ſort of ſuch Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and they are altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any Knowledge, either from Ancients or Moderns; only know how to let blood, give a Purge or Clyſter; when any ſuch is called to a Patient, he never ſtands to enquire into the Diſeaſe, but preſently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines this to be done, and that to be taken upon pain of life, and if it ſucceed well, then he is a very skilful man; but if ill, then there was no other courſe to ſave his life; and plead the former excuſes. Theſe I do as much pity for their ignorance, as blame for their too raſh confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; 'tis probable if they knew better they would act wiſer.</p>
            <p>There's another ſort, much akin with the former, but carry things
<pb facs="tcp:66140:22"/>
more modeſtly, and bring this fetch to excuſe their ignorance; they tell the ſick, they ſaw the ſame Diſeaſe cured (in ſome remarkable place, and by ſome eminent perſons, 'tis like they tell them) and they have the means wherewithal it was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and ſeveral times ſince have tried it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall ſay by theſe and the former, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> did when he ſaw ſome <hi>Rodians</hi> gorgeouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel'd: Tuſh, ſaid he, that's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but pride, and ſeeing ſome poor <hi>Spartans</hi> ſtand by in their thread bare Caps; ſaid, that's but another ſort of pride. There are many other ſuch Jugglers that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have been decoy'd by, which are palliated with heavenly excuſes to blind your eyes; I ſhall ſpeak but of one more, which is the greateſt and moſt dangerous of all; and that is, in procraſtinating and retarding Cures. They will undertake any thing, though they know nothing
<pb facs="tcp:66140:22"/>
(as to a Cure) yet in keeping them in hand ſo long by their deluſions, in promiſing this time, and that time, and tell them of Spring and Fall ſo long, till the Patient is fallen: if any ſuch <hi>Hocus</hi> be asked either by the Patient or ſome other Friend, what he thinks of his Diſeaſe, or Ulcer; he tells them, there is no danger, and that by ſuch a time he may be well, and when that fails, then puts it to another time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now if any ingenious Patient be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſmell this Juggler, and apply himſelf to ſome able and honeſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, to mend what he marr'd; but whether it may be accompliſhed by Art, or not; This Quack-ſalver hath this fetch to excuſe his deceitful ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, if the Patient be recovered, then ſaith this Impoſtor, why I knew and told him ſo, that there was no danger at all, and that he would be well, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but if it cannot be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Art, then ſaith this deceiver,
<pb facs="tcp:66140:23"/>
if he had continu'd with me, I could have cured him (I ſhould not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it) long before this time and there was no danger in it, when he went from me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is the Devil's <hi>Hocuſt Pocuſt,</hi> that he teaches ſuch Artiſts to perſwade people, the neareſt way to Heaven, is by way of Hell; that groſs Impiety and grand Hypocriſie, that ſuch Juglers are guilty of, they commonly lay on the ſhoulders of the Innocent.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry to ſpeak it, that I have ſeen too many ſuch deluding ſouls in this Country; I ſhall forbear to ſpeak any more leſt ſome ſhould think I ſpeak in prejudice: I proteſt the contrary, but wiſh them really ſuch, as they would have the World underſtand them to be: I expect ſuch as I have touched the guilty conſcience of, to ſnarle againſt me; who will endeavour to corrupt your Judgment, and perſwade you into an ill opinion of this ſmall Piece (for
<pb facs="tcp:66140:23"/>
whoſe good it was deſigned by the Author) raiſing, it may be, curious and malitious Queſtions amongſt you, as the Rabbies and Doctors did amongſt the Jews, <hi>viz.</hi> Can there any good thing come out of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth?</hi> and that he eats and drinks with the Publicans; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I tell ſuch, 'tis better be a Publican amongſt the Phariſees, than a <hi>Judas</hi> amongſt the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>My laſt advice unto you is this, whatſoever good this, or any other may bring unto you, return all your praiſes unto that God from whom you receive all your Mercies.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Foelix quicunque dolore</l>
               <l>Alterius diſcet, poſſe carere ſuo.</l>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <signed>R, C.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <pb facs="tcp:66140:24"/>From my Houſe at the Sign of the <hi>Globe</hi> and <hi>Chymical Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces</hi> in the <hi>Poſtern</hi> near <hi>Moorgate.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Febr.</hi> 4 1679/80.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Chr. Pack.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JAmes Pemberton</hi> (Son in law to Mr. <hi>Rowland Pippin,</hi> ſo famous for curing of all curable Ruptures, or Broken Bellies) liveth at the Sign of the three <hi>Naked Boys</hi> on <hi>Ludgate-Hill,</hi> where he undertaketh the Cure of all curable Ruptures, and maketh all ſorts of Truſſes fit for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of any. His Wife treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Women; they give Advice for nothing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:24"/>
            <head>A TABLE of the ſeveral Diſeaſes and Diſtempers treated of (amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things) in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing TRACT.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FEvers in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</item>
               <item>Malignant Fevers in Children.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Directions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Heat in Fevers.</item>
               <item>Cold in Fevers.</item>
               <item>Thirſt in Fevers.</item>
               <item>Agues.</item>
               <item>Dropſies.</item>
               <item>Falling-Sickneſs</item>
               <item>Griping of the Guts.</item>
               <item>Surfeits.</item>
               <item>Fluxes.</item>
               <item>Stone or Gravel in the Reins or Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys.</item>
               <item>Windy-Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</item>
               <item>Wind in the Small Guts.</item>
               <item>Collick.</item>
               <item>Wind-Dropſie.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:66140:25"/>Gouts.</item>
               <item>Pleuriſie.</item>
               <item>Yellow Jaundice.</item>
               <item>Stone in the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</item>
               <item>Conſumption with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Cough.</item>
               <item>A Conſumption with a Cough.</item>
               <item>The Rickets.</item>
               <item>Apoplexy.</item>
               <item>Vertigo.</item>
               <item>Palſie.</item>
               <item>Convulſion.</item>
               <item>Cramp.</item>
               <item>Worms.</item>
               <item>The breaking of a Vein.</item>
               <item>Coughs, Catarrhs, Rheums &amp; ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Breath.</item>
               <item>Strangury.</item>
               <item>Fits of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66140:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Praxis Catholica:</hi> OR, THE COUNTRY-MAN'S Univerſal REMEDY.</head>
            <p>IT was the cuſtom amongſt the ancient Greeks, that if a ſure Cure was found for any Diſeaſe, the party was bound to write it on a Table, and hang it up in the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> that every one labouring with that Diſeaſe, might afterwards repair thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and receive their Remedy.</p>
            <p>Soon after did they digeſt the Art of Healing into a fatal Method, as a Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the true knowledge of Curing;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66140:26"/>
whereby a further enquiry into Medicines came to be neglected, and ſo this falſe Doctrine of the Greeks ſpread it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Arabians, Romans, and then amongſt the Chriſtians, and is ſtill in uſe amongſt us to this day, to blind us from the knowledge of true and perfect Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for curing our Diſeaſes; whereby we ſee many yearly ſwept away from us, through ſome accuſtomed Diſeaſes, as well as new ones, and eſpecially that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Children, of a Griping, Vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Scouring, which gives me great cauſe to miſtruſt, that either the true cauſe of this is not underſtood as well as the reſt, or a fit Remedy not yet found out.</p>
            <p>Nor is it Children alone, that this Fever, the Prince of Diſeaſes, doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unto in thoſe bloody manners, but to ſome of full Growth and Strength. It doth aſſault us in various Shapes and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits. This Diſeaſe is a grand Enemy to man; for there is hardly a Diſtemper but is accompanied with a Fever, either going before, or following after it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſhall a little anatomize it unto you, and ſhew you its Riſe, the place where it commonly abides, and what it feeds on, and ſo deſcribe it as you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66140:26"/>
may know it at a diſtance, and not only this, but moſt of our Serpentine Enemies.</p>
            <p>I ſhall obſerve that method in treating of them, as I do in curing of them; which is, to have reſpect unto that firſt which doth moſt preſs; amonſt which, I think that peracute Diſeaſe of Children is moſt ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, ſo my method leads me to begin with a child, whom I ſhall trace unto his old age, where I ſhall leave him to that great Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, whoſe Servant I am not worthy to be.</p>
            <p>Firſt it will be neceſſary that I give a preparative (to your underſtanding, in unfolding the right uſe of two or three principal parts, whoſe proper uſes have not yet been diſcovered) before you enter upon the main Body; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>The Spleen.</item>
                  <item>Liver: and</item>
                  <item>Gaul.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe three comes Life and Death, Health and Diſeaſes, as they are diſpoſed, either well or ill. Theſe are the Pillars that do ſupport the Fabrick of the Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm.</p>
            <p>The two firſt do principally reſpect the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66140:27"/>
preſervation of Health; the laſt is of a more Balſamical Nature, which doth as well prevent Diſeaſes, as reſtore health when it is wanting.</p>
            <p>Underſtand by a Ferment</p>
            <p>A Specifical Virtue or Power which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part is endued withal, that whatſoever is transferred through them is transmuted into their fermental quality,<note place="margin">Omnis facultas quando praeva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let ea est natura ut mutet ſibique ſimile faciat id quod ad ipſam est victum.</note> as the Aliment in digeſting in the Stomach is ſow'r; then, when the Chyle paſſeth through the Guts, <hi>Duodenum</hi> and <hi>Ileon,</hi> it is ſaltiſh, and being more elaborated in the <hi>Meſeraick</hi> and Milky Veins, becometh more ſalt, which is a preparation for Sanguification, which is perfected in the Liver, and ſo aſſimilated by every part.</p>
            <p>The whole Body is ſeaſoned and tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Ferments of thoſe three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal parts, <hi>viz.</hi> ſharp from the Spleen,<note place="margin">Whitmore de Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre anomala.</note> Salt from the Liver, and bitter from the Gaul. To begin with the firſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66140:27"/>
               <head>The Spleen.</head>
               <p>This part hath been hardly cenſured by many to be the receptacle of the <hi>Faeces</hi> of the Blood, the mother of black Choler, or Melancholy, the Sink and Fountain of many ſtubborn and rebellious Diſeaſes, and to be a Bowel of no great uſe; only to elaborate this more feculent Blood, and give a ſmall nouriſhment to ſome of the natural parts: likewiſe the efficient cauſe of Madneſs and Dotage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some have not ſtuck to ſay, that if ever nature made any thing to hurt her ſelf, it was this, and if ſhe had found out ſome other way for diſcharging of this Excrement, as ſhe hath done the reſt, ſhe had eaſed her ſelf of abundance of trouble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther think the contrary, there is not any part within us, nature hath been ſo liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al unto, as to this, nor hath beſtowed ſuch ſpecial favour on:<note place="margin">Vide Dr. High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more de affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Hypochon. fol. <hi>132.</hi>
                  </note> it is enriched with ten times, at leaſt, as many Arteries as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other part.</p>
               <p>There is life peculiarly due unto it more than ſenſitive; for it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66140:28"/>
extant long before quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.<note place="margin">Helmont. de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. duum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rut.</note> It hath a double Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; there is a Vital from the Arteries, and the dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive faculty of the Stomach which is made by an acid juice ſent from it; and for that great concernment which is committed unto its charge, it is termed the Preſident of the Stomach. I cannot think that any excrementitious matter can reſide, where it hath ſo worthy a place for its Emunctory, as the Stomach; the Arteries fetch from the Stomach of their pureſt Chyle, and ſanguifie it for their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and it may be by their too liberal at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, may debilitate their Ferment, that ſo they may require an aſſiſtance from the main Body, whereby the Stomach may be neglected, with a due quantity of this juice; whence lack of appetite and crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties do ariſe, and ſo this Ferment may be exorbitant in the Spleen; from whence comes bloody and black ſpitting into the ſtomach (which ſome have judged black Choler) which is nothing but an expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and renewing of nouriſhable blood from the Spleen it ſelf; the Humour, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy and black Choler was never yet found in nature, nor indeed is there any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66140:28"/>
ſuch thing extant: wherefore whatſoever diſtemper may ariſe from the Spleen, it is from a vitiated or debilitated Ferment: not from a peccant matter, which doth offend only in quality, not in quantity.</p>
               <p>Again, if the diſtemper of the Spleen be the cauſe of Madneſs, then in its right order, there is a ſound and judicious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding due to the ſame place: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Maxim of the Ancients, <hi>Ejuſdem partis atque poteſtatis ſit functio ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, cujus eſt vitiata ac viciſſim,</hi> i. e. <hi>There is a ſound function of the ſame part and power, whereof there is a vicious one, and on the contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could ſpeak much in defence of the Dignity of this noble part, but at preſent ſhall conclude with this: the great Offices that proceed from it, and that rich and noble Retinue that attends it, ſpeaks it no leſs than the pallace where the ſenſitive ſoul keeps her Reſidence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Liver.</head>
               <p>I ſhall but only hint at this becauſe I ſhall ſpeak more largely of it when I come to treat about Dropſies, and other Diſeaſes that are falſely fathered on it: what a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66140:29"/>
common complaint is there about a hot Liver, and a cold Stomach: when as I ſhall demonſtrate, that the Liver is never hotter than is neceſſary, nor the Stomach never colder: though it may ſeem ſo by imperfect or weak digeſtion.</p>
               <p>And although Sanguification is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in it, yet it is the perfecter and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of it: whereby the Blood is aſſimila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and conveyed into every part through the Veins. In a word, the Liver is the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator to all the natural parts in man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Gaul.</head>
               <p>In the firſt Diſeaſe that I ſhall ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I ſhall be enforced to anatomize this Bowel, only by the way take notice, that this Gall is the great Balſom of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as well for preventing and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Diſeaſes, as the curing our Wounds.</p>
               <p>Underſtand, that whatſoever is done by nature (in any thing of this kind) is performed by this great Balſom: nor hath this as well as the reſt been free from the Calumniations of the ignorant, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it guilty of cauſing ſeveral ſharp Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But more of this in the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:66140:29"/>
               <head>Of Fevers.</head>
               <p>I Shall ſpeak a word in general, then come to particulars, all Fevers are of the ſame eſſence and name: and differ not ſo much in the matter as place.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Place.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Place</hi> it acts in, is the Stomach moſtly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Cauſe</hi> is from the error and eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Faculties; or from things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted and untranſmuted; or elſe from Excrements not being rightly ſubdued, or ſeparated, and orderly evacuated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Diviſion:</hi> there are two ſorts, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and intermitting.</p>
                  <p>From the firſt there are ſeveral Species, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome very malign; others accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with leſs Malignity: others with none at all.</p>
                  <p>Intermitting ones, are of three ſorts (Legitimate) <hi>Quotidian, Tertian</hi> and <hi>Quartan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66140:30"/>Not to trouble you to treat of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious and peſtilential Fevers: none hath yet been amongſt us, God ſtill keep them from us, and remedy them where they are.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall therefore begin with malignant Fevers, which are very rife in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, eſpecially amongſt Children.</p>
                  <p>A malignant Fever differs from a <hi>Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> or Burning, or any other Fever in this, that it draws its putrefaction imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from its own matter: for indeed putrefaction is joyned with it.</p>
                  <p>A burning Fever, and other Fevers do not derive their putrefaction immediately from their matter, but gradually and caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally either from the peccancy of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or debility of the Ferment where it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, thoſe are of a leſs malignity, and bound in a leſs quantity of the matter of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ephemera,</hi> or an one days Fever is more from a diſpoſition or inclination to a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe; for that morbifick matter in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach is ſoon caſt up by Vomit, or digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I rather call it a Diſtemper than a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>But more particularly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:66140:30"/>
               <head>A Malignant Fever in Children.</head>
               <p>AS I have ſhewed that a Malignant Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is from the preſent putrefaction of its own matter;<note place="margin">Parvae Febres quandoque val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de malignae, Hipp. Diagnoſt.</note> ſo this violent Diſeaſe in Children is of that nature, which is clearly demonſtrated from the Symptoms in the firſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault; that within forty eight hours pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction hath been nigh perfected, as is perceived by a coldneſs in the extreme parts, and cold ſweats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p>It is from ſome thing received which may contain ſome vicious quality, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in quantity; or from an ill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the digeſtive Ferment; for it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happens, that when the ſeaſon is moſt hot, then the digeſtion is weakeſt, and then crude Fruits, and things hard to digeſt take advantage of the ſtomach:</p>
                  <p>But above all, I look at Milk and Sugar
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66140:31"/>
to be the greateſt cauſe; for Milk is the general Food of Children, and there is ſuch a propenſity in its own nature to cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, that if it be not quickly digeſted, it obeyeth the acid Ferment of the place, which ſoon is coagulated, and a Curd made like new tough Cheeſe, which doth ſtrongly reſiſt digeſtion, eſpecially in a weak and tender ſtomach, and if it be not ſpeedily vomited up, it ſoon begets a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefactive Ferment, and then ſoon after thoſe terrible Symptoms are produced, as Vomiting, Scouring, Griping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Natura morbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum est medicus medicus naturae miniſter.</note>Now Nature, which is the Phyſician to Diſeaſes, unites her force, and takes with her a quantity of this Gaul-balſom to rectifie this Malignity, and eradicate the Morbifick Matter; and whatſoever this Balſom doth incorporate with, it hinders its putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as Salt doth in Fleſh or Fiſh) and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons it with its taſte, and colours it with its tincture, as a little Wormwood doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing it is commixt with, and a little Saffron doth Milk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what part of it is ſeparated for its putrefactive Body, nature endeavours to caſt forth, and by reaſon it ſtill retains its acquired ſharpneſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66140:31"/>
from the putrefactive Ferment falling down upon the <hi>Pylorus,</hi> or lower mouth of the ſtomach, ſtirreth up thoſe violent motions; and what part of it paſſeth through the Inteſtines, it abſtergeth and ſcoureth away that mucous or phlegmatick matter which nature hath lined the Guts withal; for a twofold end: firſt, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Obſtructions, that the Chyle may have a more ſpeedy and ſlippery paſſage: Secondly, to defend them from any ſharp or corroſive quality that may be in the Chyle, which is transferred through them.</p>
                  <p>Which ſlimy matter is commonly ſeen to ſcour from them in this Diſeaſe, and this being gone, this excrementitious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth eaſily corrode by its ſharpneſs, which is the cauſe of thoſe Tortures and Gripings.</p>
                  <p>And in regard that this peccant matter which is caſt forth, is tinctured by this Balſom, it hath deceived many, who have taken it to be the Gaul itſelf.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, there are Excrements in Children, from eating Milk, not perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſted, which are of this Tincture, but of no bitteriſh Taſte, it is browniſh in the ſtomach, yellow in the Ilion, and green
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66140:32"/>
in the blind Gut, yet they may not be ſick.</p>
                  <p>And no marvel, that there is little or none of this Balſom found in its Recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or Bladder in dead Children; for if this be ſpent, Death immediately follows, according to that Proverb:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When the Gaul is broken, the drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Carcaſe riſeth to the top of the Water,</hi> when it can no longer withſtand putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe Sacrilegious Jews knew that this Gaul was a great Cordial for the preſerving and continuing life; wherefore they gave our Saviour Vinegar and Gaul: Vinegar to excite the faculties of the ſtomach, for the Gauls quicker paſſage into the vital ſpirits to prolong his life, that they might the longer torment him under his pains before death.</p>
                  <p>But to ſtay no longer here, it follows in the next place to treat about the great Heat and Cold which happens by Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, as well in moſt other Fevers as in this; and likewiſe of that inordinate Thirſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66140:32"/>
               <head>Of Heat.</head>
               <p>THough Heat and Fever are counted Synonyma's of one and the ſame name, individual companions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet I ſay, this Heat is not of the Quiddity or Eſſence of the Diſeaſe, neither is it the cauſe of any Diſeaſe, but is cauſed by the ſtirring up of that vital aiery ſpirit, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectoreſs of life; which ſpirit it is that makes the aſſault:<note place="margin">Archaeus Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Hippoc.</note> now this ſpirit being provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the Diſeaſe, allarms all the Faculties, Virtues and Powers both Vital and Natural, which it doth unite unto it ſelf, and ſo furiouſly aſſault his mortal Enemy, as many Coals of Fire raked together, and blown up, make a great heat, ſo doth this heat proceed from this inflamed Spirit.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EXAMPLE.</head>
                  <p>A Thorn or Splinter being got into the Finger or Hand, preſently a heat, pain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66140:33"/>
and pulſation is felt, which this ſpirit or <hi>Archaeus</hi> ſtirreth up, for the expelling of that extraneous Body: now this heat is not a product of the Thorn, but caſually from this ſpirit, and occaſionally only from the Thorn: therefore heat is a latter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and ſubſequent upon the eſſence of a Fever.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cold.</head>
               <p>COld is the Diſeaſes Colours, or Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, under which it fights, but it is not either the Diſeaſe, nor Cauſe, but a product and effect of the Diſeaſe,<note place="margin">Calorem &amp; fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus non eſſe mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ut neque bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſas. <hi>Hipp.</hi>
                  </note> putrefaction brings in coldneſs, the Ferment of Putrefaction is ſharp and cold: as we have an ocular Demonſtration in Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grenes and Mortifications, whilſt it is but in <hi>fieri</hi> a Gangrene, what a hard task it is to revive it by the hotteſt and moſt penetrating Medicines we can get; nay,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66140:33"/>
and fain to ſcarrifie deeply too, leſt it ſhould hinder their operation; or if it fouls a bone, no leſs than a Medicine that is hot in the higheſt degree can effect it, and when a <hi>Sphacelus,</hi> or Mortification is confirmed, without natures Second comes in ſpeedily to her reſcue,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Chyrurg. naturae mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> and diſmember it, it would ſoon run her to the heart; and did not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction work by a cold, a Body would be hotter after it was dead, than it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but we ſee the contrary, when pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction grows ſtronger, the Body grows colder: I could evidence by many demonſtrations more, that the Heat is not of the eſſence, neither the cauſe, nor oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a Fever, and likewiſe, that Cold is meerly the effect of the Diſeaſe: but I think this ſufficient.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Thirſt.</head>
                  <p>This great Thirſt in Fevers doth not proceed from Heat and drineſs, as in a true and natural Thirſt; for this will not be allayed by drinking, as that will; but this Thirſt is deceitful, and is produced by ſome excrementitious matter, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66140:34"/>
adheres to that ſenſitive faculty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes the Organ,<note place="margin">Nec ſitis eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tincta prius quam vita bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndo.</note> as if a great dryneſs had ſuddenly come unto it, as I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in a very malignant Fever, which the Army in <hi>Flanders</hi> was infected with, being always cold, and very thirſty; as likewiſe in the cold Fit of an Ague, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo this is evident, that heat in Fevers is not the cauſe of that inordinate Thirſt; beſides I have extinguiſhed this Thirſt by thoſe things which have been virtually hot;<note place="margin">Contraria con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariis curan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> which, if heat had been the cauſe, would rather have exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</p>
                  <p>Thus you have the matter, manner, and Concomitants of this Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>The Schools have obſerved ſome Heads, from whence they have derived many Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Fevers, (which I ſhall not inſiſt on, becauſe they depend upon one and the ſame way and means of Cure) without mention of an Hectick, or intermitting Fever, which differ only in the place they reſide, which I ſhall ſpeak to in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per places.</p>
                  <p>It is my chief deſign to do good unto my
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66140:34"/>
Countrymen, who (I know) would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have ſomething to eaſe them, and be rid of their Diſeaſes, than to hear curious and learned Diſcourſes, or quaint Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions; and in pleaſing them, I care not whom I diſpleaſe.</p>
                  <p>As I have put the knowledge of the cauſe into your Heads, ſo I ſhall put a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy into your Hands.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cure.</head>
                  <p>You may clearly ſee what firſt is to be done, and wherein the Cure doth conſiſt, which is, in removing the cauſe or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter offending; the neglect whereof hath ſuffered ſuch an infinite Slaughter, which gives me reaſon to think, that either the cauſe is not known, or a fit Remedy not yet found; for unleſs there be a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the Remedy and the Diſeaſe, It will do but little good.</p>
                  <p>Diſeaſes which come ſuddenly, if they are rightly underſtood, they are ſoon gone,<note place="margin">Extrema non permanent.</note> though they may be extreme ſharp whilſt they continue.</p>
                  <p>I know it is the practice here to look more unto the Effect than the Cauſe, in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66140:35"/>
correcting the Symptoms than the matter whereof they are produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced;<note place="margin">Si ta tollantur quae conveniunt aeger melius ſe habet &amp; facile ſert: Sublata cauſa tolletur effectus.</note> which is a very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious courſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto reaſon, and all principles in Healing.</p>
                  <p>And that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtand your error, I ſhall recite your practice.</p>
                  <p>When firſt any one is taken with this, or the like Diſtemper, either Child, or thoſe of full Growth, firſt you run and fetch Mint Water, and a little Syrup to ſtay the Vomiting.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, then Cinnamon Water and Syrup of Quinces, or Myrtle Berries to ſtay the ſcouring.</p>
                  <p>Then, it may be, you give a Carmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or Clyſter to expel Wind, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Griping.</p>
                  <p>That done, you give ſome cooling Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lep to allay its Heat, and to quench in Thirſt.</p>
                  <p>And when it is cold, you give a little Mithridate, or Theriack of <hi>Andronica,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>London</hi> Treacle, and lay a Plaiſter of it to his Stomach.</p>
                  <p>And then lay a Spell againſt the Fever to the Wriſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66140:35"/>And ſo you keep doing, till you can do no more; juſt as a man who hath loſt himſelf in a Wood, he keeps going, but whither he knows not.</p>
                  <p>You ſee all thoſe things do but reſpect the effect, here is nothing hath any regard at all unto the Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>And ſhould things anſwer the intention for which they were given the party, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Child or Man would preſently die.</p>
                  <p>To hinder the evacuating of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick matter, is directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the intention of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;<note place="margin">Quo natura ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ad locum conferentem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eo ducere oportet. <hi>Hippoc.</hi>
                     </note> for the evacuation of this matter is to be looked at as the <hi>Criſis</hi> of Nature, and whoſoever ſhall reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, all this matter is to be brought out, and whoever goes about to ſtop it in the beginning, works againſt nature. What a vain thing therefore is it to think to take away the Gripings, before the matter be gone that cauſes it; and to corroborate the ſtomach, or to refreſh its Spirits, ſo long as the Enemy beareth ſway.</p>
                  <p>To give the Child Mithridate, or lay a plaiſter of it to the ſtomach, which is worſe, becomes another Diſeaſe; or any thing elſe that is nauſeous, whilſt Nature &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66140:36"/>
the Diſeaſe are ſtruggling: and to give cooling things to correct the hear, is to weaken nature and ſtrengthen the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But you will tell me many have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the uſe of thoſe means.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> And many more had been, had they never been uſed (with ſubmiſſion to providence) but <hi>(quoad homines)</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of men, I admire that any ſhould recover that ever was affected with this Diſeaſe, for they are ever giving, and all to hurt it; ſeeing the beſt Friends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the worſt Enemies, which makes good that old Saying,
<q>
                        <l>When God cuts off man's thread of life,</l>
                        <l>His deareſt Friends do bring the knife.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But many things are wrought by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as we have known many have been recovered from a Fever by drinking cold water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> From whence ſome have aſſerted, that this Heat is of the Eſſence of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> But this Cure is not wrought by the Water, as it is cold and moiſt, for Sack or ſtrong Beer would have performed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66140:36"/>
it, and a great deal better; but it is from the great quantity of it, which doth ſo replete the ſtomach, that ſome of the peccant mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which doth adhere unto the Fibres thereof, the Water hath looſened, and ſo its brought away with it.</p>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe whoſoever hath been cured by Water, it hath been when the Diſeaſe hath been on him ſome conſiderable time, and not in the beginning. I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Water ſeveral times in the end of a Fever, to this intent, and I ever found it very ſucceſsful; but I ſuppoſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that have taken it upon their own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual inclination, it was hap-hazard with them, for to take Water in the beginning of a Fever, either kills them, or ſtrikes them into an Ague, or ſome other long Sickneſs.</p>
                  <p>To drink it in a contagious, peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Fever, or any Fever that tends much to putrefaction, haſtens death.</p>
                  <p>I do not ſpeak this as not approving of the uſe of Water; but I declare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for I have found as ſtrange events by drinking Water, as ever I ſaw by any Phyſick. I have known a man cured very ſoon of an <hi>Atrophia,</hi> or Conſumption, only by the drinking of pure Rock Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66140:37"/>
and in many other caſes have I uſed it: but great conſideration is to be had in the giving of it.</p>
                  <p>But to return, by applying a nauſeous or foetid Medicine to the Stomach, whilſt the morbifick matter reſides there; nature thinking ſhe is aſſaulted by another Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, unites all her ſtrength and force, and deſperately attempts both her Enemies with this reſolution, to extirpate them, or ſink her ſelf, whereby ſhe may, by exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating of her new Enemy, caſt forth the old, and then this amongſt the ignorant is cryed up for a laudable Medicine, when as ſuch things are done by chance, for where one hath recovered by this means, twenty have died.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee what a blind courſe hath been taken for the curing this, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſeaſe. The meer pity that I bear to poor Infants, hath extorted this from me, to whom I have often been ſent for, to ſee them die, when their ſpirits have been ſo far ſpent, that I have not dared to give them any thing to take off the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, to the great grief of my ſpirit, for without the Diſeaſe be taken away, to ſmall purpoſe do we uſe Cordial Means to refreſh their Spirits.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66140:37"/>
                  <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
                  <p>I ſhall now direct you to a better way, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. When you are aſſured this Diſeaſe is on them (which is known firſt by a ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring away of a ſlimy matter, then a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colouring of the Excremenrs, as yellow, green, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and a griping in the Belly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very hot and cold by Intervals: preſs not any manner of Meat upon them,<note place="margin">Impura corporae quo plus nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris eo majus laeſeris.</note> as you ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lives; this very thing hath deſtroyed thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. For to give Meat whilſt the Diſeaſe is on them, when the ſtomach is not fit to receive it, nor hath ſtrength to digeſt it, without it be ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vomited up again, it becomes a Recruit, or ſupply to the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Neither adminiſter, nor apply any thing external, or internal, that is any way nauſeous or ungrateful to the ſtomach, for nature hates and abhors ſuch things; for though it be laid upon the ſtomach,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66140:38"/>
yet the taſte of it is in the ſtomach, as though it were contained there, eſpecially in young and tender Skins; for to have a thing that is nauſeous to the ſtomach, and ungrateful to the ſmell, conſtantly to lie on, would be troubleſome to one that is in health, much more to him that is ſick. Give not the Child any Milk, and if it ſuck, wean it; for Milk is the firſt matter and foundation this Diſeaſe is raiſed on, and it bears ſtill an affinity with it, and is preſently converted into its poiſonous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and likewiſe let it forbear Water and Beer, either cold or warm: keep the ſick party (either Child or otherwiſe) in a breathing ſweat, which is done by drinking warm Poſſet-drink, the Milk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turn'd with White Wine, or Sack, or Beer ſharpened with Vinegar; let the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty drink of it as warm as he can take it: this is far better than any Cordial or Julip whatſoever in a putrid Diſeaſe, between whiles the Child may drink a good draught of Sack, raw, and without Sugar is beſt; and if it tends to coldneſs, either in Face, Noſe, Hands or Feet, you may ſafely give it a liberal draught of Brandy, with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle white Sugar, though the Child be not two months old, and likewiſe make a Toaſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66140:38"/>
of old ſtale Bread, or a piece of Roſe-Cake, and ſoak it in warm Brandy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a little white Sugar hath been diſſolved, and put it to the Child's Stomach, and let it lie on for twenty four hours, and if the coldneſs is not removed, you may reiterate it. I have a ſpecifick Water for that end, which doth much revive and cherriſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>What though it exaſperateth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more hot? That is well recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; for it mightily ſtrengthens and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth nature.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve, that a hot and feveriſh tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is the moſt laudable and beſt temper the Child can be in, whilſt the Diſeaſe remains.</p>
                  <p>When the morbifick matter is gone, you may give a little ſalt of Pearls; Corral, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or Wormwood, which are very good in a Cordial Electuary, to kill that putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factive Ferment in the place where the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe lay, that may lie behind lurking; which is the cauſe of moſt Relapſes, and long and tedious Sickneſſes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions.</p>
                  <p>'Tis not enough to remove the effect, or matter produced, nor the cauſe produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, but the principal producer muſt be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66140:39"/>
rectified before health be perfectly reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have directed you in the beſt courſe you can take; and be ſure you will do nothing that will hurt, but rather to ſtrengthen and refreſh nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But you will ask me, what ſhall we do to remove the cauſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is the principal Verb in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I know a more proper and ſafe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine to effect it, than I can direct you unto, in all the Diſpenſitory. 'Tis true, there are a great many good Medicines, though good for little, without it be the <hi>Laudanum</hi> of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and ſome few Chymical Preparations: the reſt are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worth a man's knowledge.</p>
                  <p>That Phyſician that hath not found out better and more ſpecifical means than what are there, is like to make but a ſad pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
                  <p>But I ſhall ſpeak it to your comfort, God hath given me the knowledge of ſuch a Medicine as will effect it; and not only this, but it doth alſo eradicate and extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the cauſe of moſt Diſeaſes incident unto our frail Bodies, as you will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perceive.</p>
                  <p>It is a Powder without either ſmell or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66140:39"/>
taſte, and the higheſt doſe or quantity is but five or ſix Grains to the moſt robuſtive or ſtrong Body, and ſo downward to half a Grain, which a Child of two days old may ſafely take, its operations are various, according to the nature and place where the peccant matter reſides. How you ſhall take it, and what is to be done and obſerved in the taking of it, I ſhall give directions in the latter end of this Book.</p>
                  <p>And as it is an effectual, ſo it is a ſafe Medicine; for I have given it unto three or fourſcore ſeveral Children in and about the Town of <hi>Boſton,</hi> and indeed I know not of any one that died, that ever took it, except one: the ſpirits of which were quite ſpent before I gave it, that it was not able to retain it in its ſtomach, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately brought it up again.</p>
                  <p>There is an eminent perſon in this Country, whoſe knowledge is great in the moſt curious and beſt <hi>Arcanums,</hi> or ſecret Medicines that are uſed, he could tell you, it is as ſafe as good, who was an eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto a wonderful operation it had in a moſt contagious and malign Diſeaſe, which was the Small Pox, which ſtruck in among the Paſſengers in Captain <hi>Lord</hi>'s Ship, coming from <hi>England</hi> two years
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66140:40"/>
ſince, that not one died that took it, two only died, and neither of them took it, as the Chyrurgion, Mr. <hi>Whiting</hi> can teſtifie, I gave him ſome of this Powder, and bade him give to every one that was infected with that Diſeaſe, which he did accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; though he gave it to ſome that was blind, to others after they appeared twenty four hours, and very ready to be ſuffocated, and very ſoon made them all perfectly well, which was well known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Paſſengers in the Ship, as well as unto themſelves that took it, which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated through this Country; and I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but this Paper will find out ſome of them, who can well witneſs this truth.</p>
                  <p>By this you may judge of its efficacy in any other Diſeaſe of a malignant nature.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall tell you what I have obſerved from it in ſome other Maladies.</p>
                  <p>I have cured all ſorts of Fevers with this <hi>Arcanum univerſale,</hi> in all Ages and Sexes; for continual burning Fevers, whether putrid or not, are frequently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off by it with one Doſe, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or at the moſt by two, ſo that the Patient may be well before the time of the expected <hi>Criſis.</hi> The ſame Benefit I have often obſerved when given in the ſtate of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66140:40"/>
the Diſeaſe, that it hath been preſently taken off, although then nature is obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to take a longer time to renew the ſtrength, than ſhe would have needed, if ſhe had been aſſiſted with this Medicine in the beginning. How common a thing it is to make a Month or ſix weeks work in curing a Fever, although peradventure nature it ſelf hath overcome the Diſeaſe in twelve or fourteen days, but the diſeaſie matter formed, and ſome ſymptoms of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects muſt entertain the Phyſician a great while longer. For if the Fever were pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid, then the Stomach and Lungs remain loaden with much pituitous matter, to carry off which, the common practice is to follow the Patient cloſe with Expectora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſuch are their Pectoral <hi>Electuaries, Decoctions, Syrups, Lohochs,</hi> &amp;c. the which are ſo far from anſwering that end, as really to add to the matter they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to expel, for they not being <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents</hi> impowered to alter or rectifie any Ferment, as ſoon as they come into the Stomach, either nauſeate it with their Load, and ſo are caſt up, or if they ſtay, ſubmit to the depraved digeſtion of the Stomach, and there make an increaſe of the diſeaſie matter, whence an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66140:41"/>
ſpitting continues till nature it ſelf, by degrees retrieves the natural Ferment, and frees her ſelf from the diſeaſe matter, and the pretended remedy together. But if this ſeem too long a doing, (that no piece of Art may be wanting) there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way at hand, and that is to exhibit purging Medicines to carry it downwards, the which is more pernicious than the former, for the Purge drawing a great quantity of ſordid matter from the <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax</hi> to the Guts, and nature not having yet recovered her right Regiment may admit ſome of this matter (by the Meſeraick or Milky Veins) again into the Blood, whence may ſucceed again a Fever <hi>de novo,</hi> called a Relapſe, or (if the lately tired ſpirit take not the preſent Aſſault) then the occaſional cauſe of a <hi>Dropſie, Hectick,</hi> Conſumption or ſome other Cronick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes: All which is eaſily prevented by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Doſe or two of this <hi>Arcanum,</hi> which evacuates the preſent matter by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and rectifies the vitiated Ferment of the Stomach, and other parts, whence the power of making ſuch matter is quite taken away. This I have had very large experience of. But a few days before the writing of this, I was ſent for to a luſty
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66140:41"/>
young man, who had laboured under a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochus,</hi> about a week having, for during that time been treated by an Apothecary, firſt with cooling Juleps, which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all the while, then ſtrongly ſweat by a Sudorifick, and the next day blooded; but the Diſeaſe notwithſtanding increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (as being newly changed from a <hi>non putrida</hi> to a putrid, when I came) made the Apothecary, it ſeems, weary or doubtful of his work; for he deſired the Man's Wife to ſend for a Phyſician, or a Second, (who was a Friend of his, 'tis like for the Bills ſake) but the Woman ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving formerly had ſome experience of my Medicines, ſent to me about five or ſix that Afternoon, I preſently ordered him four Grains of this Powder, which wrought once only by Vomit, and diſcharged the ſtomach of that Diſeaſie matter, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore felt to him like a great weight, the pain in his Head preſently abated, and that night he reſted pretty well (for he had no ſleep worth mention ſince he was ill) the next morning I ſent him four Grains more of the Powder, which gave him three Vomits and two Stools: about ſix in the Afternoon I went to viſit him, and found him about his Chamber, ſaying, he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66140:42"/>
thought he was as well as ever, his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach being returned, and he very hungry. Thus you ſee a Fever cured in eighteen hours, or leſs, which in all probability would have been at the leaſt three or four weeks (if recovered at all) before nature by ſuch enfeebled helpers, or rather, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers (as are the common Medicines) could have freed her ſelf from the Diſeaſe. I could inſtance many the like caſes were it needful. This Medicine hath (beſides its other gifts) ſuch a general tendency for the curing of all Fevers, that upon the firſt knowledge of it in practice, I called it my <hi>Species Febrifuga,</hi> by which name I publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in my Catalogue of Medicines, Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the year 1676, although I had then ſeen this little Book of the Authors. I ſhall here ſubjoyn a ſhort Diſcourſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitting Fevers or Agues, in which Mr. <hi>Couch</hi> is ſilent, except in the name, yet I cannot doubt but he muſt be well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the power of this Medicine in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:66140:42"/>
               <head>Of Agues.</head>
               <p>GReat Diverſity hath been, and yet is among Authors concerning this Diſeaſe, ſome holding one thing, and ſome another concerning its Seat and Cauſes: but I without reciting their differences or contending with any man's opinion (either of which is no way profitable) ſhall brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour to give you my own ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It needs no <hi>Definition,</hi> being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known here; neither <hi>Diviſion,</hi> ſeeing all the ſorts thereof proceed from one cauſe, and may be cured by the ſame Medicines.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Seat.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Place</hi> or <hi>Seat</hi> of Agues is the <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas,</hi> or <hi>Sweet-bread;</hi> for all the parts of Man's Body being conſidered, which only by intervals may tranſmit the cauſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitting Fevers to the Heart, none is found to which not only the <hi>Focus</hi> or ſource of thoſe Fevers, but alſo the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66140:43"/>
of all their Symptoms may be aſcribed, beſides the <hi>Pancreas</hi> or <hi>Sweet-bread.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Cauſe</hi> is an Obſtruction of one or more of the Lateral Ducts or Branches of the <hi>Pancreas,</hi> by reaſon of Phlegmatick Matter carried thither in too large a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and there detained, the which being ſeparated from the Blood (together with the Pancreatick Juice) by the Glandules of the <hi>Pancreas,</hi> and ſent to the main Duct or Pipe thereof cauſeth an Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, and detaineth the juice of the <hi>Pancreas</hi> (contrary to nature) which ought continually to flow into the thin Gut, called the <hi>Duodenum.</hi> This Juice being thus ſtagnated, quickly grows acrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or ſharp, and acquires a putrefactive Ferment, whence at length it makes way through the obſtructing Phlegm, and is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into the <hi>Duodenum,</hi> where meeting with the Bile or Gall, it ſtirs up a vicious and preternatural Ferment, from whence comes the Ague Fit with all its Symptoms, as in the beginning, horrour, chilneſs, cold, ſhaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then preſently reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yawnings and vomiting of bitter or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66140:43"/>
four reliſh, and afterwards burning heat, the cauſes of <hi>Heat, Cold, Thirſt,</hi> &amp;c. you have in the foregoing Chapter of Fevers: but if any deſire further ſatisfaction, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reaſons of the differences of Agues, and the conſtant or various acceſs of their Fits with the particular cauſes of Symptoms, they may read it at large in <hi>Regnerus de Graaf,</hi> in his Book intituled, <hi>de ſucco Pancreatico,</hi> publiſhed by me in the year 1676, to which I refer the Reader, not having room here to be any larger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cure.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Cure</hi> conſiſts in opening the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, changing the diſeaſie Ferment, and expelling ſuch matter as the Diſeaſe hath rendred incapable of being redinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grated and taken into the communion of life. All which intentions are truly and radically performed by this <hi>Powder;</hi> for an Ague being removed by the due uſe of this Medicine, returns not again, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaves any danger of its degeneration into another Diſeaſe, both of which too frequently happen after the uſe of ſome Medicines which take off the Fit only by a kind of ſoporiferous quieting the preſent
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66140:44"/>
fury of the <hi>Archaeus.</hi> If it be taken before the Ague hath exceeded three Fits, one only Doſe is uſually ſufficient to carry it away; if fix or ſeven Fits, two Doſes or three at the moſt; yea, I have cured di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers at twice or thrice giving it that have had it ſix or eight weeks; but if it be a year old or more, the continuance of its uſe but a reaſonable time (with the help of the Balſamick Pill) will not fail to cure it. I have alſo known it to cure A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues when it hath had no other ſenſible o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration than Breaking of Wind.</p>
                  <p>A perſon living in <hi>Greenwich</hi> who had a Tertian Ague, and ſometimes a Quotidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an all the laſt Winter, was cured this Spring by three Doſes of the Powder which never had any ſenſible operation, and two Doſes of the Balſamick Pill, ſo that in eight or ten days he was abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Affairs, and never had any Fit ſince, although he was before ſo low brought, that he could not ſit up any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than while his Bed was made, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the conſtant advice of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Phyſician of that Town, which he had uſed.</p>
                  <p>It is to be taken in a Spoonful of Drink, or Poſſet drink about an hour before the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66140:44"/>
Fit comes, for two or three Fits together, according as the Ague is in continuance. If the Patient be weak, or of a tender ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Body, let him take a Doſe of the Balſamick Pill the ſame night after the Powder hath been given, when he goes to Bed, with a draught of warm Ale, or a Glaſs of good generous Wine, which Pill will mightily corroborate and refreſh his Spirits, and alſo tends much to the Cure, if the Ague have been of a long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or be a Quartan, or fourth Ague, then after the Patient hath taken the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three times, if the Fit ſtill remain, then let him take a full doſe of the Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Pill, two or three hours before the coming of the next Fit, and goe to Bed, and diſpoſe himſelf to ſweat before the Fit comes, the which if he do, its ten to one but the Fit comes no more; but if there ſhould be a failure of ſweating timely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, then let him take the powder be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one Fit, and the Pill before the next, till it be gone; but not one Ague in twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will need to be thus treated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:66140:45"/>
               <head>A general Direction in Fevers.</head>
               <p>TO drink liberally of ſuch Liquor as is moſt convenient, is good: I like not Beer of any Liquor in a Fever, before the peccant matter (wherein the Diſeaſe doth ſubſiſt) be evacuated, becauſe it hath a nutriment from the Grain it is made withal, which doth add unto the matter of the Diſeaſe, whereby Thirſt is exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, as is commonly ſeen.</p>
               <p>I rather adviſe to drink Wine and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, two parts Water, and one Wine, ſharpened a little with the Spirit of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol, or Sulphur, if it be <hi>per campanam,</hi> which is drawn from a Bell Still, it is the better, which is a ſingular Medicine to allay and correct the inordinate Thirſt and Heat in Fevers. <hi>Medera, Fial, French,</hi> or <hi>Sherry</hi> Wines, you may uſe, <hi>Malaga</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sweet Wine is not ſo good, neither Syrups, or any Sugared or Honeyed Meat, or Drink<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And when they begin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> plaineſt Broths and Gruels are the beſt; till then a little is too much,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66140:45"/>
and if you did uſe Salt and Vinegar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Spices and Sugar, the ſick would like it the better; and it would be better for them; a few Prunes and Currants, if the ſick like them, may be uſed.</p>
               <p>But ſome may ſay, How ſhall we do that live far up the Country, where we have no Wines, nor can get neither of thoſe Spirits? the beſt that I can adviſe you to, is Milk boiled, and turned with ſome Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar or Verjuice, the Curd being taken away, whereof he may drink freely, but he is to take it alway hot, and the hotter the better.</p>
               <p>This courſe is to be taken after the cauſe is removed by my powder, or ſomething elſe (but I know not what) otherwiſe this, or any other, is like to do but little good.</p>
               <p>Bleeding, Purging, Clyſters, Cordials, Juleps, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are but Trifles in curing a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, they do at beſt but correct the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms or Effects; I will do more good with one doſe of my Powder, and one of my Pills, than they with all thoſe in a Month.</p>
               <p>If the Fever be continual, and come by a Surfeit, or otherwiſe, ſo that the Patient
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66140:46"/>
feel a Load or Weight at his Stomach, or hath a propenſity to vomit, the firſt thing to be done is to give a Vomit, whereby the Stomach and firſt paſſages may be freed of the groſſeſt of the Diſeaſie Matter wherein the Fever ſits, or hath taken up its Inn, to which purpoſe you may give <hi>half an ounce of the Infuſion of</hi> Crocus Metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, or ſix Drams, or a whole Ounce (according to the age and ſtrength of the Patient) in a ſmall Draught of warm Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-drink; but if you know any better An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonial Preparation, then give it. That being done, ℞ <hi>Tartar. Vitriolat ſix Grains, Volatile Salt of Amber and Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn, each ſeven or eight Grains, mix them, and give the mixture twice a day in a little thin Broth, or Water Gruel.</hi> This is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſive and Diuretick, and will cleanſe the Stomach and Inteſtines of the remaining Sordes, and expel them by Urine. For the Feveriſh Thirſt give the dulcified Spirit of Nitre, or of Salt, in Poſſet drink, and all the Liquids they take, from five or ſix to ten or twelve drops at a time. Keep the Patient in a ſmall breathing Sweat, either with the Poſſet-drink, before-mentioned by Mr. <hi>Couch,</hi> or with <hi>Treacle-water</hi> and Powder, or rather the Tincture of <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66140:46"/>
Snake-root,</hi> or which is moſt excellent (if you can get it) the <hi>Aqua Prophylacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca of Sylvius de le Boe,</hi> of which <hi>Take three Ounces, Water of Carduus and Borrage, each one Ounce, Syrrup of Citron Peels an ounce and an half, mix them, and take it often by a ſpoonful or two at a time.</hi> But inſtead of this, if the Fever be malignant, give <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoardicum minerale</hi> to eight or ten Grains every third or fourth hour in a ſpoonful or two of good Canary.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the <hi>Aqua Prophylactica</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned is rarely to be had at any ſhop, I will here deſcribe the making thereof for the ſakes of thoſe who are willing to make it. ℞ <hi>Roots of Angelica, Zedoary, of each an ounce, Butterbur two ounces, the leaves of Rue four ounces, of Balm, Scabious and Marygold Flowers, each two ounces, unripe Walnuts, cut two pounds, freſh Citrons cut one pound. Let them be all beaten together, and pour upon them ſix quarts of the beſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled Wine-Vinegar, let them ſtand in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion all night, and then diſtil them by a very eaſie fire (without burning) till they be dry, and keep the diſtilled liquor for uſe.</hi> It is very profitable in all Fevers, eſpecially in thoſe which are malignant and the Plague.</p>
               <p>In the declining of the Fever, if ſleep be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66140:47"/>
wanting, this following mixture will much avail, both to cauſe reſt, and refreſh the Spirits, ℞ <hi>of Treacle water an ounce, the thin Syrup of Corn Poppies, an ounce, or an ounce and a half, Laudanum Londinenſ. or rather that of Paracelſus two grains, mix them, and let the Patient drink it at the hour of Sleep.</hi> But give nothing wherein there is Opium or Poppies in the beginning of a Fever, becauſe they tie up the <hi>Archaeus</hi> of the Stomach and firſt paſſages, thereby hindering him from ſeparating and expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the occaſional cauſe of the Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Agues,</hi> or intermitting Fevers, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>Quotidians, Tertians</hi> or <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> proceed as followeth:</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Of Salt of Amber twenty grains, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum Vitriolatum ſix grains, Diagridium ſeven, eight, nine or ten grains, according to the ſtrength of the Patient; mix them into a Powder, and give it in a little Poſſet-drink, or thin Broth, four or five hours before the time of the Fit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Repeat it two or three times, if need be; but if the Ague be not then gone, give the following mixture about an hour, or an hour and an half before the Fit comes; the Patient being in Bed, and diſpoſing himſelf to ſweat.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66140:47"/>℞ <hi>of Carduus Water two ounces, Treacle Water two drams, Salt of Wormwood half a dram, Spirit of Salt Armoniac ten grains, Syrup of Corn Poppies half on ounce, mix.</hi> This, if the Patient ſweat well with it, frequently removes the Ague.</p>
               <p>This following alſo hath cured many without any other Medicine.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of the Salt of Wormwood and Carduus each fifteen grains, Tartar Vitriolat. ſix grains, Sugar of Pearls half a dram; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and mix them, and give it half an hour, or an hour before the Fits acceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Juice of Featherfew being drank (about half an ounce) in a glaſs of Wormwood Wine, is profitable againſt the Quartan or fourth Ague.</p>
               <p>Theſe Remedies I have uſed with good ſucceſs, but never found any thing ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and effectual in Fevers, as my <hi>Species Febrifuga,</hi> and <hi>Pillula Balſamica.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:66140:48"/>
               <head>A Dropſie.</head>
               <p>There are three ſorts of Dropſies, <hi>viz. Anaſarca, Aſcites</hi> and <hi>Timpanites</hi> the two firſt are moſt from Water. The laſt, Timpany is more from Wind.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anaſarca,</hi> is when the extreme parts ſwell; but when the Belly, then it is <hi>Aſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cauſe, I do not believe, (as hath generally been received) that it proceeds from a Diſtemper of the Liver, and that to be the principal part affected; but I have more reaſon to think it to proceed from an obſtruction or impediment in one of the Kidneys: for commonly they that are troubled with Gravel and Stone in the Kidneys are Hydropical; and ſeldom any that have been affected with either <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarca</hi> or <hi>Aſcites,</hi> but they have obſerved a Dolor in their Reins to precede it; and ſo that Water which ſhould be transferred through the Kidneys, to be evacuated by the Bladder is forced out at the <hi>Abdomen.</hi> And it hath lately appeared by diſſection,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66140:48"/>
that thoſe who have died of thoſe Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, the fault hath been through the Kidney, which is moſt agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>And undoubtedly that operation in an <hi>Aſcites,</hi> in making a hole to let out the Water, doth but only reſpect the effect not taken away, (and yet not inconſiſtent to that Maxim, <hi>Take away the cauſe, and the effect ceaſeth:</hi> which is to be underſtood of that which is to come, and not of what is paſt, as <hi>Helmont</hi> well obſerves) and ſo that operation might happily perfect a Cure in taking the effect for the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>I have cured a man of an <hi>Anaſarca,</hi> (whoſe Thigh hath been near as big as his middle) with one Doſe of this Powder he was preſently made perfectly well; that in the operation of this Medicine, his Legs &amp; Thighs fell, and never ſwelled after, you would have admired (had you ſeen) what abundance of Water came from him, both by Urine, and Vomiting; and at night I gave him a Pill (which I uſually do after this Powder) to refreſh his Spirits, and ſeetle his Body in a right temper.</p>
               <p>This was all the Phyſick he took from me, though he had ſpent many pounds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in fruitleſs endeavours. And I know
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66140:49"/>
not any thing to the contrary, but it may do as well in an <hi>Aſcites,</hi> or <hi>Timpanites,</hi> if it hath not continued too long.</p>
               <p>Firſt it is neceſſary to begin the Cure with gentle purging; for ſtrong Purges, (eſpecially in weak and tender Bodies) do far more harm than good, by reſolving and expelling the Blood, and good juices with the peccant matter, thereby deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtrength, and depauperating the vital ſpirit.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of the Roots of Orris an ounce and a half, Parſley Roots half an ounce, Leaves of Agrimony a handful, clean Senna an ounce, beſt Rhubarb half an ounce, Agarick three drams, Cinnamon two drams, Cloves one dram, cut the Roots, with the Rhubarb and Agarick into thin ſlices, bruiſe the Spices, and put them all into a little Bag, infuſe them twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four hours in two quarts of the beſt White or Rheniſh Wine, then let the Patient drink e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning five or ſix ounces, or as much as will give four or five Stools.</hi> It is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to take; but if you pleaſe, you may alſo add Sugar to it.</p>
               <p>For ſuch as had rather take Pills, thoſe following are good.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>Roſin of Scammony and Jallap, of each
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66140:49"/>
half a dram, Tartar Vitriolat, Mercurius dulcis of each two ſcruples, Oil of Juniper Berries twenty drops, of the pureſt Venice Turpentine a ſufficient quantity to make the powder into a Maſs for Pills:</hi> the which make into thirty ſmall Pills, and give three, four or five of them, according to the Patients Age and Strength every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. After purging,</p>
               <p>The Salt of Broom or Amber, of Bean-ſtalks, or of Pidgeons dung are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, either of them being taken twice a day in warm Broth, or which is better, the Spirit or Volatile Salt of humane U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine. In a Tympany the dulcified Spirit of Nitre is excellent, being taken in Broth or Sack three or four times a day, from ſix to twelve drops at a time.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman, a Friend of mine, living in <hi>Greenwich,</hi> cured a man of the Dropſie with the Pill alone. This man had an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue firſt, which either went off it ſelf, or were moved by ſome common Remedy; about ſeven weeks after which, he began to ſwell, and alſo was ſorely afflicted with Gripings and Flux for a great while, which had brought him ſo low, that he had not been out of his Bed for three weeks. The firſt Doſe of the Pill that was given him
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66140:50"/>
took away the Gripes, and in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſtayed the Flux; but then he ſwelled ſo much in his Breaſt, that he could not lie down in his Bed, but his Breath would be gone, the ſecond Doſe freed him from that, and made him able to riſe and dreſs himſelf, and by a ſhort continuance of it was cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Epilepſie, or Falling Sickneſs.</head>
               <p>I Had a Maid ſince I came to this Town, that was turned over from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no one cared to have her, by reaſon ſhe was violently troubled with the Falling Sickneſs: at length I bought her, to whom I gave only one doſe of this Powder, which freed her from her Fits, though ſhe had them before almoſt continually, day and night, that whoſoever had her, kept one to watch her, for ſhe would be ready to deſtroy her ſelf; I kept her about a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a year, and ſhe never had a Fit that I know of. I perſwaded her to take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66140:50"/>
Doſe two or three days after, but ſhe would not; ſhe told me ſhe needed not, for ſhe was confident ſhe was perfectly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Since I hear ſhe is married ſome where in the Country, and whether ſhe had them ſince, I know not</p>
               <p>By the operation of this Medicine I judged by what came from her, that the primary cauſe was not in the Brain, but in the Stomach, or ſome place near adjacent thereunto; and that the Brain ſuffered on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by conſent.</p>
               <p>Purging in this Diſeaſe (when it is ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) ſeldom or never doth any good, as alſo Blood-letting, but both are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious, as many have found to their great prejudice. But when it proceeds from the Stomach (as may be known by the Patient, perceiving in himſelf a pain, ſoreneſs, and diſtention about the mouth, or pit of the Stomach and Heart-ſtrings, eſpecially when they are faſting) before the Fit they have a diſpoſition to vomit, with pain and palpitation of the Heart, and the Fit ends with vomiting, in ſuch, I ſay, a Vomit may be available, either with the infuſion of <hi>Crocus Mettallorum,</hi> or the Salt of Vitriol; but they are warily
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66140:51"/>
to be adminiſtred, and not without the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of a Phyſician. All ſour and ſharp things are hurtful in this Diſeaſe, as Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Lemons, Vinegar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the time of the Fit you may uſe the following Lini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to anoint and chafe the Temples, Noſtrils, Wriſts and Coronal Suture, or Seam of the Skull upon the top of the Head.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Nervinum two ounces, melt it gently in a Gally pot, then put to it Oyl of Amber and Roſemary of each two drams, Spirit of Sal Armoniack, one dram, ſtir them well together, and uſe it warm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of Oil of Tartar per deliquium an ounce, Salt of Harts-horn and Amber each a ſcruple, mix them, and let the Patient take from ten to twenty drops in Broth, or Black-cherry Wine four times a day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The dung of a Peacock, or Liver of a Raven being gently dried, and powdered, and given twice a day to two Scruples, or a dram at a time are very good, but it were better, if their Volatile Salts were extracted.</p>
               <p>But the Flowers of <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> excel all the reſt, being given three times a day, from ten to fifteen or ſixteen grains at a time in Broth or Sherry Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:66140:51"/>
               <head>Tortura Ventris, or a great Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</head>
               <p>THere was a poor Fiſherman that lay down by the New Meeting Houſe in this Town, that had undergone moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Gripings and Torture in his Guts, with a great Flux and Vomiting for ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al days, till at length his Spirit was almoſt ſpent, his Belly was ſo inflated, that he could hardly breath. About ten or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Clock at night I was ſent for; I knew there was not any Medicine I had would do him good, or preſerve his life, but this Powder; I being not very well, and much diſpoſed to Sleep, told them, I would come and ſee him again as ſoon as it was day, and then I would give him ſomething. When I returned home, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered he could not live till that time, and if not quite dead, yet could not be in a capacity to take any thing, I preſently went to him again, and gave him five grains of this Powder: within half an hour after he took it, he broke wind up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66140:52"/>
and downward, to the admiration of all thoſe that were there. A little after he had a ſtool, in which came away abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of obdurate and hard excrements that a long time adhered unto his Guts, (and was the cauſe of his ſickneſs) and preſently he went to ſleep (which he had not before for ſeveral nights) and ſlept very ſoundly till the morning. The next day when I came up to ſee him, I found him up, and at Breakfaſt, and was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for his going to Sea: he told me he was as well as ever he was in his life.</p>
               <p>A Surfeit is a <hi>praeludium</hi> to at Fever, which doth not always proceed from the quantity of Meats or Drinks, but it may be from a vicious quality of Meats, as crude Fruits, Pulſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or from an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy or loathing of Meats, that the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach abhorrs; and they are ſuch things as commonly the eating of them hath made them ſick before; and ſometimes it comes by lying with their Stomachs bare when they ſleep, eſpecially in the Summer: I have known many that have beeen ſurfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and could not tell how they got it. I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew this Powder fail to make them well in ſix or eight hours.</p>
               <p>In the Month of <hi>May</hi> this preſent year
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66140:52"/>
1679, a Gentlewoman was taken with a Vomiting and Looſeneſs, which exerciſed her two days, and then of its own accord in a great meaſure ceaſed; but ſhe uſing no means to rectifie the ill Ferment of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach &amp; Bowels, and otherwiſe neglecting her ſelf, within two or three days was ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an intollerable <hi>Tortura Ventriculi,</hi> or tearing pain in her Stomach, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Hypochondriack Vapours, and an almoſt total dejection of Spirits. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four in the Afternoon ſhe ſent for me, and being come, I truly found her in a very deplorable condition, having cryed out ſo much by reaſon of the inſufferable pain ſhe felt, that ſhe had very little Breath or Voice left to crye out any longer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides almoſt her whole Body was cold, and bedewed with a clammy ſweat, her Pulſe very little, and ſometimes wholly ceſſant, ſo that at firſt ſight I did not think it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that ſhe ſhould eſcape death; but I with all expedition got ſome of the Balſamick Pill diſſolved in a good Cordial Vehicle, to which (for the Vapours ſake) I added a little of my <hi>Elixir Hyſtericum,</hi> and ſo gave her the mixture by two ſpoonfuls at a time, about twice in a quarter of an hour, continuing half an hour, in which time ſhe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66140:53"/>
was twice or thrice ſeemingly dead for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a minute at a time, at the end of the laſt ſhe vomited up the Medicine with much ſlimy matter, upon which her Pulſe began to return, but her pain being ſtill intolerable, ſhe diſpaired of help, but I being encouraged by ſome ſecond conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, and confident of the certainty of my Medicine in ſuch dolorous Affects turned up an Hour-Glaſs, and promiſed her (God aſſiſting) that ſhe ſhould have eaſe before the Sand was run, the which (to the praiſe of the Almighty) I effectually performed within the time, for I plied her quick with the Medicine, &amp; in half an hour ſhe began to grow warm in the extreme parts, and (as her ſelf expreſſed it) felt the pain go down out of her Stomach into her Belly, and to leſſen, and that ſhe could fetch her Breath from the bottom of her Belly, in an hour ſhe was in a fine tranſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring heat all over her Body, and the pain quite gone, notwithſtanding I was ſtill forced now and then to repeat the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine; for otherwiſe ſhe would feel ſome twitchings and girdings in her Stomach, threatning a return. I ſtayed with her till near twelve at night, at which time ſhe was diſpoſed to ſleep, the which ſhe did
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66140:53"/>
but two hours, and then was called up to lay a woman (ſhe being a Midwife by practice) the which ſhe went over the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to do, and came home again to Bed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight in the morning, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained very well ever ſince.</p>
               <p>For the Griping of the Guts I do not think this Balſamick Pill hath its equal in nature. How many grown People as well as Children expire yearly in this City of <hi>London,</hi> by this tormenting Diſeaſe, for want of a good Remedy. I do ſeriouſly profeſs, I do not think that any perſon need periſh by that Enemy, had they but this Medicine in time; for it commonly takes it away at one Doſe, but with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond I never failed in my life; for it will certainly give eaſe in the moſt violent Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings in two hours time, given in a large Doſe; and if the pain return, it may be repeated after eight hours; but where there is ſtrong Vomitings alſo, it is beſt to give it diſſolved in warm Ale, or Sack, and ſo give it by a ſpoonful or two at a time, and very often, that ſo the ſtomach may not caſt it up before it comes to operate, for it will ſtay the Vomiting and Looſneſs as well as eaſe the Pain, the which ought to be done with all expedition (unleſs the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66140:54"/>
Diſeaſe proceed from a Surfeit, then firſt give a Doſe of the Powder) let ignorant people think what they will, who often out of a fooliſh timeroſity ſuffer them ſo long, till the ſtrength is ſo exhauſted, that it cannot be again reſtored; and ſo they as miſerably as fooliſhly ſhake hands with their lives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FLUXES.</head>
               <p>THere are three ſorts of Fluxes, <hi>viz. Lienteria, Diarrhoea</hi> and <hi>Dyſenteria:</hi> and Authors have very confuſedly treated of their Cauſes, and their Places; and becauſe they would be ſure to hit right, they have named almoſt every place. But the cauſe of the firſt, <hi>Lienteria,</hi> is from a defect of the Spleen, which doth not ſend a ſufficiency of that acid juice into the Stomach, which maketh the digeſtive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, whereupon it is, that the meat comes away with little alteration.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> is from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66140:54"/>
of the Meſaraick Veins, that do not attract the Chyle, whereby it is evacuated as Excrements.</p>
               <p>The laſt, <hi>Dyſenteria,</hi> is from Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that adhere to the Inteſtines, and by their Acrimony corrode, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee that they proceed from ſeveral Cauſes, and yet to be cured by one Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Every one may judge it to be an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canum Catholicum,</hi> or an univerſal Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which I know this Powder I tell you of hath perfectly effected, as I have well experienced. And in this laſt I common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give my Balſamical Pills the next night, to conſolidate the Excoriations which the morbifick matter hath cauſed.</p>
               <p>In all Fluxes of the Belly, whether bloody, or not, you may do as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Firſt give half a dram, or two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or a dram of the Powder of Toaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rhubarb, mixed with a little Conſerve of Red Roſes, and made into a Bolus. Then ℞ <hi>of the Conſerve of Red Roſes &amp; Mint of each an ounce, Orange Pill candied ſix drams, Red Coral in fine Powder a dram, Diaſcordium two drams, Syrup of Myrtles ſufficient to make a ſoft Electuary, let the Patient take it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66140:55"/>
often about a dram at once.</hi> Or this: ℞ <hi>of Mint Water, and Cinnamon Water, each an Ounce, Plantane Water two ounces, Syrup of Comfrey an ounce and an half, Laudanum two grains, mix them, and let the ſick take it by a ſpoonful every half hour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Flux with the Griping of Guts, as alſo in others, this following is very good. ℞ <hi>of the beſt Cinnamon Water three ounce, of Diaſcordium three drams, let them be well mixed, and give it by two ſpoonfuls at a time pretty often.</hi> Either this or the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer will both ſtay the Vomiting, and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the Flux.</p>
               <p>The following Clyſter is alſo good to alleviate the ſharpneſs of the matter, and eaſe the excoriated Guts. ℞ <hi>of new Milk half a pint or better, in which quench a piece of red hot ſteel once or twice, to which add half an ounce of Venice Turpentine diſſolved in the yolk of an Egg, Honey of Roſes an ounce, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Balſam of Sulphur ten or twelve drops mix and make a Clyſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pill alone will cure any Flux or Looſneſs whatſoever preſently, yea the Bloody Flux in two, three, or four days, according to its magnitude, but in that caſe it is good to continue the uſe of it a day or two after the Flux is ſtayed, leſt the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66140:55"/>
Acrimonious Ferment (not being quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed) ſhould reaſſume its force, and cauſe the Diſeaſe to return. Therefore in ſuch Countries where this Malady is in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Epidemical (as <hi>Ireland,</hi> and perhaps ſome other places) did they but know the worth of this Pill, they would undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly prize it at a high rate, and reſcue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a miſerable perſon from the devouring jaws of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Calculus Renum; or, Stone or Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel in the Reins or Kidneys.</head>
               <p>THe Stone or Gravel in the Reins or Kidneys, as it is the ſharpeſt of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, ſo it hath been the longeſt in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, though the preſent Fit or Pain is ſoon remedied. I never knew any Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was paſt forty five, or forty ſix years of age that was ever perfectly cured, but once or twice a year after, they have been troubled with it more or leſs; though I knew a Gentlewoman that was free from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:66140:56"/>
any Fit nigh two years, and then aſſaulted her again as violently as at firſt.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe Paroxyſms or Fits that come by Intervals, which are ſo dolorous, do not proceed from the Gravel or Stone genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but from the Kidney generating, which may be affected either primarily, from a debility or vitiouſneſs of its own Ferment, or caſually, from an exceſs in quantity, or being too ſharp or ſalt in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: and in regard it is ſo ſenſible a part, muſt needs ſtir up an inflammation, which maketh thoſe cruel Tortures. And ſhould all the Gravel and Stone come away, the pain would not be the leſs, until the Kidney it ſelf be reduced to its right temper. For we ſee how vain and uſeleſs all thoſe things have proved, that have been given to abſterge, and force away the Gravel and Stone, nay, they have much more exaſperated the pain, and made it more.</p>
                  <p>And beſides that, the Gravel and Stone are not the cauſe of thoſe Tortures, I find by this Powder, which hath perfectly freed them from all their pain in two or three hours, and no Gravel or Stone hath
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66140:56"/>
come from them, neither that day, nor the next.</p>
                  <p>Again, how many have I ſeen in perfect health, that have voided a great quantity of Gravel at a time, without the leaſt pain, it would be in one as well as in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>By any Weakneſs, Conſumption, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, or any Diſtemper of the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Gravel may be cauſed, ſo that Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel is the product, not the producer or primitive cauſe of this pain.</p>
                  <p>In this Diſeaſe the Belly is to be kept looſe; which may be well performed by this following. ℞ <hi>of the Pulp of Caſſia, newly drawn four ounces, Tartar Vitriolated, two drams, powder it, and mix; to the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, add ten or twelve drops of oil of Juniper.</hi> Take of it once in three or four days at night going to Bed, at each time ſix drams, or an ounce, which will give two or three Stools the next day.</p>
                  <p>Then give the following Powder. <hi>Take of Tartar Vitriolated a dram and a half, Crabs-eyes, Salt of Bean-ſtalks, of Broom, of Reſtharra, and Pidgeons dung each two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, mix and make a Powder.</hi> The Doſe is a ſcruple or more twice a day in Parſley or
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66140:57"/>
Saxifrage Water. When the pain is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, and the Urine ſtopped, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing potion may be given to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſick. <hi>Take of fine Venice Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine waſhed a ſcruple, diſſolve it in the yolk of a new laid Egg, by beating them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then put them to a quarter of a pint, or half a pint of new Milk, and let the patient drink it off at once.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wild Carrot Seed being boiled in Ale, and the Ale drank two or three times a day, is good both to hinder the increaſe of the Stone (by reſiſting the putrefactive ſtonyfying odour or Ferment,) and alſo to diminiſh it being grown, but its uſe muſt be continued a Month together at the leaſt. The German <hi>Academ. Curios.</hi> in their firſt Volumn publiſhed in the Year 1670 <hi>obſervat.</hi> 107. highly commend the Decoction of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Bettony for expelling the Stone, being drank in a large quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and continued for ſome time; an example of which is there ſet down at large, of a certain Woman who was freed from a Stone in the left Kidney, by the uſe of the ſaid Decoction, after it had been her miſerable Companion for ſixteen years.</p>
                  <p>The Pill being taken in a full Doſe, and diſſolved in a Glaſs of well warmed White
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66140:57"/>
or Rheniſh Wine (or where that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, Ale) and ſo drank, gives pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eaſe in the moſt grievous pains, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by Stone or Gravel in the Kidneys, when all other Remedies fail; and I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member once a Gentlewoman that I gave it to, either at the firſt or ſecond Doſe voided three Stones of an untoward Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, with much pain, and remained free from that tormenting dolor (with which ſhe was wont to be often exerciſed) for the ſpace of three years. But for the Stone in the Bladder, I do not know that either the Powder or Pill will do any thing, as to the Cure, only give ſome preſent eaſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Flatus Hypochond. or Windy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy.</head>
               <p>ANd likewiſe there is the Windy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, that many, both Men and Women in this Country are troubled with, (eſpecially thoſe that live near the Sea) I will not ſay, that if the party hath been
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66140:58"/>
troubled with it above a year, it is not to be cured; but I never knew it cured: Though this Powder of mine is the beſt thing that ever I uſed for it, it gives them ſpeedy eaſe, and much corrects the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Malady. And one that hath not been above a year troubled with it, it cures them at once taking. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Diſtemper bears an affinity with ſome other flatuous and windy Diſtempers, I ſhall treat of their cauſes together; as Coliack and Illiack Paſſion with a windy Pleuriſie and Tympany.</p>
               <p>Theſe are called windy Diſtempers (though very improperly) neither Air or Wind are the cauſe of any of them.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p>Negatively, not Air or Wind that is breathed into us, nor from any windineſs that is in Meat or Drink, that is the cauſe of thoſe Diſtempers; but poſitively from ſome malign or putrefactive or dungy quality that is contained in them, or from a vitious quality or debility of the digeſtive Ferment, or from Excrements detained beyond their due order.</p>
                  <p>There is in every Vegetive an aiery ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66140:58"/>
[or <hi>Gas</hi>] which doth defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it from putrefaction, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours its ſubſiſtence in its primitive eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and figure, which ſuffering a Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is evaporated and exhaled.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EXAMPLE.</head>
                  <p>As in New Wine, after it comes into the Cellars, it paſſeth another Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe a Raiſin of the Sun, when the aiery ſpirit which was in the Grape is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from its concrete Body, the Grape contracts it ſelf, and taketh a new Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Raiſin.</p>
                  <p>Alſo we ſee in an Apple, when it is roaſted at the Fire, this aiery <hi>Gas</hi> is exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, which was co-fermented with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  <p>In like manner all things that begin to putrefie, this aiery Spirit parts from them, and then they take another Ferment. As in poyſons, when their venemous ſharp quality ſeiſeth on the Muſcles, this aiery <hi>Blas</hi> flies from them, whence the Body tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mifies and ſwells ſo: as we ſee in Bodies that die through putrefaction, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they die, how they are oppreſſed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66140:59"/>
with this Wind, which doth puff up their Bodies after they are dead.</p>
                  <p>The windy Blaſt is made chiefly in thoſe three places, the Stomach, Ilion and Colon.</p>
                  <p>From the Stomach proceeds this windy Melancholy (as they call it) and moſt of thoſe Flatulent Diſtempers, for whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any thing is not well digeſted in the Stomach, this Blaſt is preſently made, as we ſee in this Diſtemper; whatſoever they eat or drink, how they belch for it, and are worſe commonly after they have eaten, than they were before; which doth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrate, that the principal defect is in the Stomach, and therefore not from the meat they eat, but from the viciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or defective Ferment; for let another eat and drink of the ſame, it doth not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb them at all. And to talk of windy Meats, is but a meer <hi>Chymera:</hi> there are no Meats or Drinks windy to good and healthful ſtomachs; too great repletion doth likewiſe ſtir up, and cauſe this win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyneſs in the ſtomach.</p>
                  <p>By the favour of belchings you may underſtand the temper of the Stomach.</p>
                  <p>Sour Belchings betokeneth a weak ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
                  <p>Unſavory ſheweth a weaker.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:66140:59"/>Burntiſh, bitter and ſharp ones, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a vicious ſtomach.</p>
                  <p>There are ſome Specifical, which give their own ſavour, as Garlick, Onions, Radiſhes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could ſay much more to vindicate the Spleen from having a hand in thoſe flatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Diſtempers,<note place="margin">If you would be better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, read Doctor <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, de affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Hypochond. fol.</hi> 105.</note> as alſo that air or wind that we received from without, is not the cauſe whereof they are made. But leſt I ſhould make my Book outſwell an Enchyridion. I do paſs it in ſilence: and deſiring to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious and faithful to all, and not willing to write the leaſt thing that I were not convinced of the truth of, nor give you the leaſt occaſion to ſay that I extol this incomparable Medicine beyond its merit; wherefore I muſt confeſs what's truth; I never knew them really cured in my life, if they were habitual, and of a long continuance;<note place="margin">Quo diuturnus eo difficilis.</note> nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is there any Diſeaſe, if once it be familiar to nature, that is of eaſie curation. I could wiſh, for the ſakes of thoſe that are troubled with theſe Maladies, that I had ſuch a ſure
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:66140:60"/>
Remedy to cure them after long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as this powder is to prevent them when they are in the beginning, and the ſureſt to bring the greateſt help at laſt.</p>
                  <p>I would not willingly be miſtaken by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one, nor have him to abuſe his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to think he may be as ſoon well of an old and chronical Diſtemper, as of one that hath newly taken poſſeſſion of the body. To proceed,</p>
                  <p>This Diſeaſe hath great affinity with the Scurvy, and therefore the ſame Medicines are proper for both.</p>
                  <p>℞ <hi>of Crabs-eyes prepared two drams, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar Vitriolated a Scruple, Flowers of Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack a dram, Confection of Alkermes without Musk three drams, Conſerve of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Scurvy Graſs three ounces, mix them into an Electuary, of which let the patient take e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning and evening a dram and a half, or two drams upon an empty ſtomach, that is, let him faſt an hour after it in the morning, and take it three hours after ſupper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Strong Purges are injurious in this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe; but after the uſe of the aforeſaid Electuary, you may purge with the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Powder: ℞ <hi>Cream of Tartar fifteen Grains, Salt of Wormwood and Scurvy Graſs
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66140:60"/>
each ten Grains, Roſin of Scammony eight, nine, or ten grains, powder and mix them, and give it in the morning in a little warm Poſſet drink.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Elixir Proprietatis</hi> of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> is highly profitable in this Diſeaſe, being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken three times a day in a Glaſs of Sherry Wine fifteen, ſixteen or twenty drops at a time. So is alſo the Volatile Salt of Amber, being taken to fifteen grains twice a day in warm Broth. But amongſt all the Remedies I know, I aſſure you I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found any of that efficacy in this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe as my Balſamick Pill, for that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the ſharp putrefactive Ferment diſcuſſeth all windyneſs, refreſheth the ſpirits, and takes away melancholy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:66140:61"/>
               <head>Illiaca Paſſio: or, the Wind in the Small Gut.</head>
               <p>IT hath been an old received opinion, that this Diſeaſe comes from the twiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that long and ſmall Gut: but I have reaſon to believe the contrary.</p>
               <p>This great Torture is not from the wind contained there, but from an excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious matter that doth adhere unto the Illion; it is as it were glued unto it by its ſlimy matter, which it is lined withal, and in time is coagulated into a very obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and hard ſubſtance.</p>
               <p>I remember when I was in <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> there was a Soldier which was miſerably troubled with this Diſeaſe for ſome days: after general Evacuation, Vomiting, Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, then carminative and fumous Clyſters, and abundance of other means, he found not the leaſt eaſe: there was given him three or four ounces of Quick-ſilver, and that came ſoon through him, yet no eaſe: at laſt I gave him four of the biggeſt Musket Bullets I could get; about ſix or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66140:61"/>
eight hours after I came to him, and he was diſcharged of pain, and was fallen aſleep, which he had not before for ſeveral nights; after he awaked he had a Stool, wherein was two of the Bullets, and about eight or nine great round pieces of excrement, greater than the Bullets, and they did ſeem to be as hard.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it could not be wind, for it is always repleted with wind, to hinder ſuch accidents, by making the more clearer and more ſlippery way for the Chyle, and when there is a redundancy of it, it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily forced forth behind, without any Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or Torture.</p>
               <p>So you ſee it is not from Wind, or knotting of the Gut, but from ſome excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that doth adhere unto the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>COLLICK.</head>
               <p>THe Collick is commonly from Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments contained beyond their courſe, which vitiates the Ferment of the place,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66140:62"/>
whence cometh thoſe windy Blaſts, which are not wind, but far more ſubtle and rare than the moſt rarified air, being of an inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulate nature; whereupon thoſe retained excrements adhere ſo firmly to the Gut, that it contracts it, which is the cauſe of that violent dolour. I had a man that was ſhot (at the Siege of <hi>Iper</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi>) in the lower Belly;<note place="margin">Hypogaſtrium.</note> which penetrated the Colon: all his Excrements came out at his wound for about ſix days, ſo that the <hi>Inteſtinum Rectum,</hi> or Arſe-gut became uſeleſs: this wound lay twenty four hours expoſed to the wind before he was dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. I made a Suture to the external Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and cured him by vulnerary Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, how many wounds have I ſeen that have penetrated the Breaſt and Belly, and yet never troubled with thoſe windy Pains or Tortures; and yet we ſee there is hardly a Diſtemper amongſt us, but we accuſe wind, troubled with wind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the ſmall benefit thoſe diſcuſſors of wind have brought, is able to convince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that wind is not the cauſe.</p>
               <p>But indeed this aiery Blaſt, which is made by a bad digeſtion of things, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:66140:62"/>
ſeems to be wind, (which is perceived to move between the Muſcles of the ſides, and cauſeth thoſe Ructations and Belch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) hath never been thought on by the Schools, and but of very late years treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</p>
               <p>To confirm Mr. <hi>Couch</hi>'s opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Illiaca Paſſio,</hi> I ſhall here add another experiment, which is this; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a year ago a certain man was ſorely tormented with the excruciating pains of this Diſeaſe, commonly called the twiſting of the Guts, his Phyſician treated him with (I ſuppoſe) all the uſual Remedies, and ſome other Devices, one of which was I remember to blow wind into the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtinum Rectum,</hi> or Arſe-gut with a pair of Bellows, but nothing taking effect to give the miſerable man any eaſe, the laſt Remedy was inſtituted, which was three pound weight of Quickſilver, which the Patient poured down his Throat on Friday about ten or eleven in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and preſently (as adviſed) rode a little way for the better agitating of his Body, but yet to no purpoſe; for on the Sunday Morning following I was at his Houſe by accident, with another perſon,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:66140:63"/>
who was a Phyſician, and then none of the Quickſilver had made any paſſage; he had the very aſpect of death, and complained of an intollerable cold and weight in his Belly, went not to bed in three nights, and if he fell into the leaſt ſleep, nothing but dotage and diſtraction appeared, His Phyſician was at a <hi>ne plus ultra,</hi> thinking him a dead man, as all that ſaw him. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enquiry we underſtood that he was not forbid the taking of any thing, nor yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to any thing beſides Canary, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we adviſed that he ſhould abſtain from the uſe of all acids &amp; others that might have any power to coagulate any of the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver in his Body, and to drink ſweet Oil plentifully, the which he preſently put in execution, and the next day being Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, the Quickſilver began to come away like Small Shot, and the uſe of the Oil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill continued, by Tueſday night he had parted with it all, or moſt; for what they had collected wanted but four ounces of the three pounds, after which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body well adviſed him to ſwallow Golden Bullets, which he did divers times, and ſo to a wonder recovered, and is well to this day. Now had this Torture been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned only by wind, ſuch a quantity of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66140:63"/>
Quickſilver could not poſſibly have been thereby detained in the Body one quarter of an hour: or again, that it ſhould be the twiſting of the Gut, as is commonly believed, is impoſſible; for it cannot be, that the Gut ſhould be ſo cloſely twiſted up by any accident that may happen either within or without the Body, that three pound weight of this active ponderous Mineral ſhould not in three days time find a paſſage; beſides (which I had almoſt forgot to tell you) his Excrements came away with the Quickſilver in ſmall hard Bits, like dried Sheeps Dung, which plainly proves that the occaſional cauſe of this Diſeaſe is the Excrements grown to a preternatural hardneſs. I will here ſet down (for the ſake of the poor) a cheap and eaſie remedy againſt this cruel Enemy.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of the Seeds of Anniſe, Fennel, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raway and Coriander, each half an ounce, let them be all bruiſed, put them into a quart of Ale, or ſomewhat more, boil them gently in a Veſſel cloſe covered for about three quarters of an hour, then take it from the fire, and ſtrain it, and let the Patient drink half a pint at a time warm.</hi> And by God's bleſſing he ſhall ſoon have eaſe.</p>
               <p>This is alſo good in the Wind Chollick.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66140:64"/>
But the Balſamick Pill is the moſt immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Remedy for the Wind Chollick that I ever yet knew; but it is not to be given in the <hi>Illiaca Paſſio;</hi> therefore I will here, for the ſake of the ignorant, ſhew how they may diſtinguiſh thoſe Diſeaſes from one another. The pain called the Twiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Guts lies about the Navel, and higher, and is felt only before, not extended to the Right and Left Sides: that of the Chollick is about the Navel and lower, going croſs the Belly to both Sides, even to the Back, the pain gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally preſſing to the bottom of the Belly, with a ſtoppage of the Urine, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is in the former; there are ſome Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms which are common to both, as Burning, Chilneſs, Reaching, Vomiting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but what I have ſaid before is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for any to know them aſunder.</p>
               <p>A Gentlewoman living in <hi>Greenwich</hi> was lately ſeiſed with a pain in all her Bones. and a violent Looſneſs, for which ſhe took a Doſe of the Balſamick Pill, and in two hours time was at perfect eaſe, and the Looſneſs ſtopped. The next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe took a Doſe of the Powder, and at night a Doſe of the Pill, but ſleeping very ſoundly, with the Cloaths off of her,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:66140:64"/>
got cold, which turned to an Ague; after ſhe had had two Fits, ſhe took a Doſe of the Powder an hour before the acceſs of the third, and ſo was cured of her Ague, the next day ſhe fell into a Fit of the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Stone, for which ſhe took a Doſe of the Pill, which gave her eaſe, and by another Doſe the night following was quite freed. Thus you ſee divers Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (and thoſe not trivial ones neither) to be cured by the ſame Medicine. This was performed by a Gentleman in that Town that buys thoſe Medicines of me.</p>
               <p>This Diſeaſe having its Inn in the thick Guts (particularly the Colon, from whence it hath its denomination) may be eaſed by Clyſters, for which purpoſe the following is good.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of the Seeds of Coriander, Anniſe, Fennel, Carraway, each a quarter of an ounce, let them be all well bruiſed in a Mortar, then boil them in a pint of Poſſet-drink gently for a quarter of an hour in a Veſſel cloſe covered, then ſtrain it, and add thereto two ounces of Oil of Cammomile (and if you will, a little Canary, and let it be adminiſtred convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hot.</hi> If you put to it ſix or ſeven drops of the Oil of Harts-horn it will be then ſtronger and better.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:66140:65"/>The Fume or Smoak of Tobacco is a preſent remedy for eaſe, being blown up into the Guts by a Pipe put into the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament. The forementioned Drink with Seeds is alſo good in this Diſeaſe. And foraſmuch as the Chollick is many times wont to be accompanied with a grievous Symptomatical Vomiting, it is neceſſary that it ſhould ſpeedily be ſtopped, not only in regard of its own moleſtation, but alſo becauſe it hinders the retention of any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine in the Stomach, to which end uſe the following mixture.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of Simple Mint Water three ounces, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua Mirabilis an ounce, Tincture of Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon two drams, Laudanum Opiatum three grains, Syrup of Myrtles and Mint of each half an ounce, mix, and let it be taken often by a ſpoonful at a time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the violence of pain is over, purge the Body gently with this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of fine Manna an ounce and a half, Cream of Tartar half a dram in powder, mix them, and lot them be diſſolved in a draught of warm Ale, or rather Poſſet-drink, and give it in the morning faſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:66140:65"/>
               <head>Timpanites: or, the Windy Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</head>
               <p>THis Timpany ariſeth from a ſterco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous or dungy Ferment in the <hi>Saccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> or blind Gut, from Meats that are not perfectly freed from their ſtomachical ſharpneſs; and there being obſtructed, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; putrefies; from whence this foetid aiery blaſt proceeds, (indeed the worſt of all ſorts) which is breathed forth to the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritoneum,</hi> and ſo inflates the whole <hi>Abdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it is produced of ſuch a ſtinking Air, proceeding from ſome putrefied mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I am very certain; but whether it takes its Riſe from the blind Gut (as a worthy Author affirms) or from the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenterium,</hi> as I rather think, is controvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and that this dungy matter might be ſucked up by the <hi>Meſariack</hi> Veins with the Chyle: but what I am not ſure of, I ſhall not ſpeak unto.</p>
               <p>I never had one under my conſideration of this Diſtemper, ſince I had the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:66140:66"/>
of this powder; and therefore I cannot ſpeak any thing by experience in this Diſeaſe: but undoubtedly ſince it doth unobſtruct the Kidneys, and abſterge what is vitious in them, it muſt needs be good for this. And I perſwade my ſelf, whoſoever ſhall try it in the beginning of this Diſeaſe, I queſtion not but (with God's bleſſing) they will find a happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
               <p>This ſort of Dropſie is eaſily diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from others; for in this the Belly only ſwells, and is hard, not yielding to the preſſure of the Fingers, but being ſtruck upon, ſounds, after the manner of a Drum. The Cure conſiſts in changing the putrefactive Ferment of the Chyle, whether it be in the Gut, or the Veins of the Meſentery it matters not; the which being done, the inflated <hi>Abdomen</hi> ſoon falls of its own accord, for that is but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the Diſeaſe, the which neceſſarily ceaſeth, when its propagator and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is taken away. Purging is always per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious in this Diſeaſe (I mean with direct Laxatives) and therefore not to be uſed: This following is very profitable.</p>
               <p>℞ <hi>of the Seeds of ſweet Fennel, Anniſe,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:66140:66"/>
Carraway and Coriander each an ounce, Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Berries an ounce and a half, let them be all bruiſed well, and put into a Glaſs with half a dram of Salt of Tartar in powder, upon which pour a quart of the beſt Sherry Wine, ſtop it cloſe, and let it ſtand two or three days, then begin to drink of it three times a day,</hi> viz. in the morning, half an hour after dinner, and at night, at each time a ſmall Glaſs, it will be much better if you add to it a dram of the Volatile Salt of Amber in powder, which will diſſolve. When that is drank out you may put to the Ingredients a pint of Wine more, with half a dram of Salt of Amber, and it will be good. The Oily Volatile Salt of <hi>Sylvius</hi> is excellent in this Diſeaſe, as alſo in the Scurvy, <hi>Flatus Hypochondriacus</hi> and others. But the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Balſamick Pill are more certain and quick in the Cure than any other that I know of.</p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall ſpeak of Gouts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:66140:67"/>
               <head>Arthritick, or Gouty Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>THey take their names from the places they frequent, <hi>viz.</hi> Hands, Feet, Knee, or Hip, or Recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,<note place="margin">Arthriticus, Chyragra, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagra, Gona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra, Siatica.</note> and then it is called by the vulgar, the Running Gout: the Gout differeth from other Diſeaſes, for its Idaea or Character conſiſteth in the vital ſpirit, and is transferred through the Seed, (which makes it Hereditary) where it maketh a fermental ſharpneſs, which when it is exorbitant, is ſent forth into the extreme Parts, and there meeting that Callous or<note n="†" place="margin">Synovia.</note> ſeedy Glue, which is conjoyned between the Ligaments and the Bones it doth affect it with its fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental ſharpneſs, and is the cauſe of that great dolor or pain, and inflammation.</p>
               <p>It is not from humours, excrements, or blood, but a morbifick Idaea ſeminally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in the vital ſpirit, and that is the reaſon it is ſo hard to cure; for there is
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:66140:67"/>
not any <hi>Arcanum</hi> extant will reach it.</p>
               <p>Yet I believe there hath been a<note n="†" place="margin">Horizontal Gold of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus.</hi>
                  </note> Remedy found for it, and hope there will be again, when it will be more divulged.</p>
               <p>To take off a Toe or Foot doth not cure the Gout; for this pain that is exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperated, is but the fruit or product of it, for it is virtually contained in the Seed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted by the vital ſpirit.</p>
               <p>I dare not promiſe this <hi>Arcanum,</hi> or ſecret of mine to effect this Cure: yet in extremity of pain I may boldly tell you, there is not any thing will give you eaſe ſooner; and for any thing I know, it may cure it, for it will ſtrongly repel from the place.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sciatica</hi> and Knee-Gout I never yet failed to cure, with a water I make to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brocate, or waſh the part withal, though I have had ſome that one Leg was a great deal ſhorter than the other, ſo that they went with Crutches, having an <hi>Atrophia,</hi> or Conſumption in that Leg and Thigh.</p>
               <p>There is another Diſeaſe, much like, which is the <hi>Rhumatiſmus,</hi> or Running Gout, but this poſſeſſeth the muſculous part as well as the Joynts, and exulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:66140:68"/>
or breaketh out, wherefore ſome have thought it to be that Diſeaſe they call<note n="†" place="margin">Scrophula.</note> the King's Evil: I have ſeen ſeveral that have laboured with it in this Country; and without they have a Cure for it in the beginning, it brings them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Conſumption, yet I have cured one that had it twelve or fourteen years.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Place.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Place</hi> that this Diſeaſe doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly poſſeſs, are the Legs, Thighs and Hip-bones; ſometimes the lower Region of the Belly, and then it is very danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for it is of a very ſharp and malign nature, and fouls a Bone preſently, if not prevented.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cauſe.</head>
                  <p>From ſome excrementitious matter that the Meſaraick Veins have attracted, of a faetid ſavour, not fit to be transferred with the Blood, therefore the Liver diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth it into the emulgent Veins, to be carried to the Reins, and ſo to be evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through the Bladder; but the <hi>Archeus,</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:66140:68"/>
or vital ſpirit of the Reins, raiſed up with indignation againſt ſuch a fordid matter, paſſing through them, forceth it to the Legs and Thighs, (as in an <hi>Anaſarca</hi>) and ſeating it ſelf, by its vitious quality cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cure.</head>
                  <p>If this Powder be given before it hath too much defiled the place, either by foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bone, or becoming exulcerate, it bringeth it away by the Root, if not at once taking, in twice or thrice be ſure; but if it hath had too firm a footing, then it requires the aſſiſtance of ſome other things.</p>
                  <p>This Diſeaſe being ſo intimately joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the very <hi>Archeus</hi> it ſelf, hath its Inn in the moſt private Receſſes, or innermoſt Chambers of Life, into which admittance is denyed to all common Remedies, and allowed to none but the moſt powerful <hi>Arcanums,</hi> which none but the Adeptiſts have known. Therefore ſince I know not what internal Remedy to direct you (that may be had in all places) that hath power to obliterate the Character of this
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:66140:69"/>
Enemy out of the ſpirit of life, I ſhall be content to ſet down an outward applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the which (reſpecting the effect on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) doth frequently give eaſe to the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed part.</p>
                  <p>℞ <hi>Common Oil of Roſes two ounces, Oil of Guaicum and Bricks of each one ounce, mix them, and put them into a clean Pipkin, and ſet them over the fire, into which cut in thin ſlices four ounces of Caſtile Soap, ſtir it well, till it all diſſolve in the Oils, then have in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs half an ounce of Opium diſſolved in ſpirit of Sal Armoniack, which add to the other, taking it preſently from the fire, and keep it ſtirring till it be cold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which uſe as an Ointment; but if you would have it for a Plaiſter, you may add ſo much Virgins Wax when it is hot, as will give it a ſufficient conſiſtency.</p>
                  <p>The bathing or fomenting the pained part with hot Urine wherein Caſtile Soap is diſſolved doth often give eaſe; that U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine is beſt that is kept till it putrefieth and ſtinketh.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Arcanum</hi> and Pill doth certainly reſolve and expel the occaſional matter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I do not know them to be able to cure this Diſeaſe radically, but ſome I
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:66140:69"/>
have cured therewith, having it in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
                  <p>In the Month of <hi>December</hi> 1676, a Gentleman deſired my aſſiſtance, who was ſorely afflicted with the Gout, great pain and tumor in both Knees, inſomuch that he could not ſtir from his Bed to the fire ſide without Crutches for ſome weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, during which time he had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſpenſation of a Phyſician, but in no part thereof ever found any comfort, except in his promiſes: but he being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, I firſt gave him a doſe of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canum,</hi> or Powder, and at night after a doſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alſamick Pill, after which he could go croſs the Room without his Crutches: I continued the uſe of the Pill five or ſix ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and repeated the <hi>Arcanum</hi> once, and he was freed both from the pain and tumour, notwithſtanding the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the Weather, being a ſevere Froſt and Snow. But about ten days after he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving urgent buſineſs abroad, the Weather then breaking, being wet, yet cold, got a Relapſe, the Diſeaſe then returning with great pain and tumour in one foot, by the repetition of the <hi>Arcanum</hi> once, and the Pill three or four times was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reſtored, and hath ſo remained to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:66140:70"/>
this day, without any other Remedy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept two Doſes of the <hi>Arcanum,</hi> which he took the Spring following to prevent a return.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pluritis: or, Pluriſie.</head>
               <p>THis Diſeaſe is accompanied with a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, it derives its name from the place where it is ſeated, which is the inner skin of the Ribs, which we call <hi>Pleura.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The matter hath been generally receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be blood; but it is v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> doubtful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</p>
               <p>There are two reaſons from whence ſome have concluded it is blood.</p>
               <p>Firſt, By derivation, in opening a Vein on the ſame ſide, which hath immediately brought eaſe; I have done it ſeveral times.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that intention not being timely performed, then an <hi>Empyema,</hi> or Impoſthume ariſeth, through the blood there ſuppurated.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:66140:70"/>But on the contrary:</p>
               <p n="1">1. If it be from the pecculancy of the Blood that hath made an Eruption in the Veins, and extend the <hi>Pleura,</hi> whether this Blood doth re-enter the Veins, and is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuated by Phlebotomy? which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that principle, <hi>What once nature hath caſt forth, never more is received into favour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If not out of the Veins, how comes an <hi>Empyema,</hi> or Impoſthume, which is never cauſed in the Veins?</p>
               <p n="3">3. How comes this <hi>Sanies,</hi> or bloody matter, which is often ſeen in a Pluriſie, though not yet come to an <hi>Empyema?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If it be blood, how comes it to be cured by a Diaphoretick, or Medicine cauſing Sweat, which hath been often done?</p>
               <p>To treat accurately upon this Diſeaſe, would make a bigger Tract than I intend this.</p>
               <p>In a word:</p>
               <p>I have cured this Diſeaſe both ways.</p>
               <p>There is an aiery <hi>Blas</hi> contained in the Blood, which doth ſtir up and actuate it, and makes it more fluid, and ſo likewiſe there is incorporated with the Blood a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or watery matter, to contemper its Ebullition and Inflammation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:66140:71"/>But when there is a redundancy, or too much of it, or elſe when it may be too ſharp or ſalt, then this aiery ſpirit conveys it to the <hi>Pleura,</hi> to be evacuated by tranſpiration thorow it, whereby thoſe Veins are ſo repleted with this Water, that it extorts and dilates the <hi>Pleura,</hi> which cauſeth the pain in the place; and unleſs it be repelled by bleeding, or diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a ſweat; it maketh an eruption of the Veins, and the Blood iſſuing forth with it, ſoon ſuppurates, which makes an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthume, or <hi>Empyema;</hi> and although an eruption by thoſe means may be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet there may be ſome of that aqueous matter tranſpired through the <hi>Pleura,</hi> which may be tinctured with a ſanguine complexion, and cauſe that colour which is ſeen in expectoration; ſo that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the eſſence of this Malady is not blood, with ſubmiſſion to ſounder Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Now you may ask me, which of thoſe two ways I think the ſureſt: for <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſaith, a Pluriſie not perfectly cured before the fourth day, the party becometh conſumptive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I judge the morbiſick matter to be evacuated by tranſpiration through the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:66140:71"/>
                  <hi>Cutis,</hi> or Skin, to be the directeſt Courſe.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>REASONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. For ſo there is nothing exhauſted but the matter offending.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are cured by Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or Blood-letting, are more liable to that Diſtemper again.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Blood is not ſo depurated from this offenſive matter, as by a powerful Sweat.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The party affected may be in that condition, that letting Blood may prove prejudicial; as women with child, young women obſtructed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am not averſe to Blood-letting; but I had rather make uſe of my Balſamical Pill, which effects it ſingularly, and not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in any condition.</p>
                  <p>Now I am ſpeaking of letting out blood, I ſhall give my judgment in that great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, (which hath been, and is to this day controverted amongſt our great Doctors) whether it be proper in Fevers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hollerius, Forreſtus, Sennertus, Galen, Avicen,</hi> with the reſt of the Schoolmen, preſs it of a neceſſity to be done in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:66140:72"/>
                     <hi>Paracelſus, Helmont,</hi> with the reſt of the Quickſilver Wits, condemn it, as not convenient at any time.</p>
                  <p>Betwixt <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis</hi> there is a ſafe Channel, but he muſt be an experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Mariner that can ſail through.</p>
                  <p>As Practice is the beſt part of Phyſick, ſo obſervation is the ſureſt.</p>
                  <p>Errors being ſometimes admitted, do inſtruct judicious erring perſons, as good Remedies do confirm good Operators.</p>
                  <p>From my obſervation I ſhall ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to thoſe two extremes.</p>
                  <p>If I could think the School definition of a Fever true, that it is heat beſides nature, being kindled in the heart firſt, and throughout the whole Body, I ſhould think nothing could more clearly indicate Phlebotomy; but I hold the contrary, and no neceſſity for it in the beginning, but rather prejudicial.</p>
                  <p>I have been an obſerver in this Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about twenty two years, and have had many hundreds under my conſideration at once, and almoſt ſome of all Diſeaſes; and thoſe in Fevers, ſome have been let Blood, and others not; and for the moſt part, thoſe that were not let blood, were well before thoſe that were.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:66140:72"/>In any contagious peſtilential malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Fever, to let blood is very deſtructive,<note place="margin">Detracto ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine licet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puro, impurior multo, ſuccedit, Fernel.</note> as expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience well teacheth.</p>
                  <p>In a continual Fever, as <hi>Synochus,</hi> or burning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it prolongs their ſickneſs, and commonly ſtrikes them into an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Ague, or ſome other Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>In a Fever intermitting, or determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Paroxyſms, or Fits, it ſtrongly confirms them.</p>
                  <p>In a word, to let blood in any Fever in the beginning, I have found to do much hurt ſeveral times, good hardly at any time: ſo that I am inforced to ſhew my diſlike of letting blood in the beginning of this Diſeaſe. Neither do I conſent with great <hi>Helmont,</hi> the Calciner of Phyſick, and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> that Blood-letting doth exhauſt the ſpirit of life, becauſe the life is ſeated in the blood; nor that it may be convenient at any time; but I have reaſon to believe the contrary.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, Letting-blood doth never cure a Diſeaſe properly, but it doth mightily refreſh and cheriſh a weak nature that hath almoſt ſpent her ſelf, through freeing her from her mortal Enemy,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:66140:73"/>As we ſee often after a tedious ſickneſs, nature her ſelf ſtirs it up as a <hi>Criſis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quo natura verget ad locum conferentem to ducere oportet.</note> and then to take a little blood from her, doth much revive and ſtrengthen her.</p>
                  <p>I have cured a man that had a Quartan Ague above a year and four months, only by once letting blood, who never had a Fit after.</p>
                  <p>The drawing blood was but the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nature was the efficient cauſe; for ſhe was much more elevated and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened by it, whereby ſhe expunged the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick Reliques with a greater facility.</p>
                  <p>I have cured a man that had laboured with an <hi>Atrophia</hi> or Conſumption for a long time (wholly become a meer Skelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton) only by letting blood three times, about ſix ounces at a time, in the ſpace of ten days, without the uſe of any other means, he became perfectly well to the admiration of all his Neighbours.</p>
                  <p>I have ſeveral times ſince experienced it in an Hectick Fever; and although this, nor any thing elſe that I know of will cure it, yet they have been more refreſhed by it, than by all the things took; and whoſoever practiſeth it, will find it ſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:66140:73"/>I could inſtance in ſeveral more, but let this ſuffice to evidence the truth (though a Paradox) that Phlebotomy is very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtful to nature in the beginning of a Diſeaſe, but very grateful in the latter end.</p>
                  <p>The Pleuriſie is cured by Diaphoreticks and Diureticks, being mixed with ſuch things as have power to concentrate acidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as this following mixture.</p>
                  <p>℞ <hi>of the Syrup of Marſh-mallows an ounce, Syrup of Corn-Poppies an ounce and an half, Crabs-eyes prepared and Mineral Bezoar of each a dram, mix them, and make a Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, of which let the Patient lick very often till he come to ſweat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Or if he had rather have it in a liquid form, add to this Mixture Triacle and Carduus-Water of each two ounces, ſhake them well in a Glaſs, and take it by ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls till ſweat proceed. For an outward application this following is excellent.</p>
                  <p>℞ <hi>of the compound ointment of Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows an ounce, oil of ſweet Almonds and Roſes of each a quarter of an ounce, oil of white Lillies, Poppies, and Henbane ſtrained each a dram and a half, Chymical Oil of Cammomile, Cummin-Seeds and Bricks of each a ſcruple, Camphire half a dram, mix them, and make a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:66140:74"/>
Liniment.</hi> With which anoint the pained ſide as hot as it may be ſuffered.</p>
                  <p>It would grieve any pitiful heart to ſee how many perſons lives in this Diſeaſe, as well as ſome others, expire with their Blood, ſome being blooded five or ſix times over, and yet receiving no eaſe while they live, as I have divers times known. About three or four years ſince I was ſent for to a Gentlewoman, lying under this Diſeaſe, ſhe had been let blood three times, but yet had no eaſe, and was plyed with Lohochs and Linctus's, and ſuch like broken Reeds; and while I was in her Chamber the Apothecary came in with a Commiſſion to draw more blood, if he found her not eaſed. She was Patient to one of the oldeſt Doctors in <hi>London,</hi> upon which, and the conſideration of her weakneſs, I wholly declined to meddle with her, not without much reluctancy and regret of mind ſince, for my timero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: becauſe I then thought I might have ſaved life by the Balſamick Pill; and on the other hand, was confident, that ſhe would be certainly loſt by that uſage ſhe had, which accordingly came to paſs the next day, at the fifth or ſixth bloody Bout, dying under the Lancet. But I
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:66140:74"/>
never failed to cure any Pleuriſie with the Pill, by repeating it, if need be, in ten or twelve hours; I have ſometimes wholly removed the pain in two hours time, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have been twice let blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without eaſe, although I do not deny but blood-letting may ſometimes cure it without injury in ſuch as are luſty and ſtrong, or thoſe that have a <hi>Plethora</hi> of Blood. But for a common eaſie Remedy, there is none exceeds the infuſion of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dung in Ale, for it is rich in Volatile Salt, whereby it hath power to ſlay any acidity in the blood, as alſo to tranſpire any other peccant matter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ictoritia: or Yellow Jaundice.</head>
               <p>THe Schools have told us, That this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe proceedeth from an obſtruction of the Gaul-Bladder, whereby Choler is diffuſed through the whole Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helmont</hi> judgeth it to be a poyſonous Ferment beſides nature, which ſo badly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:66140:75"/>
the <hi>Pylorus,</hi> or lower Mouth of the Stomach, that the digeſtive and diſtributive faculty is alienated, and the Seat of this poiſon to be either in the <hi>Duodenum</hi> or <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon.</hi> And he proves it to be poiſonous from the inſtance of one that was bit by a Serpent, who preſently turned yellow.</p>
               <p>But my judgment doth not ſute with either; <hi>Helmont</hi> is very near it, only I think it not to be of ſo poyſonous a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as he takes it to be.</p>
               <p>This Diſtemper is often the ſequel of ſome antecedent ſickneſs, and therefore is not any primary Diſeaſe, but rather the effect or relique of ſome foregoing one.</p>
               <p>If you look back into that Diſeaſe of Children, there I tell you how the peccant matter comes to be tinctured with Choler; ſome of this matter which was morbifical in ſome precedent Diſeaſe, did adhere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Duodenum</hi> or <hi>Pylorus,</hi> which tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures the Chyle, and ſo the body becomes yellow, and a bitterneſs perceived in the mouth, I ſay, it is from the morbifick matter of ſome precedent Diſeaſe, that this Balſome of the Gaul hath coloured and ſeaſoned with its bitterneſs, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent its putrefaction, and adhering to the <hi>Pylorus</hi> or <hi>Duodenum,</hi> ſtains and imbitters
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:66140:75"/>
the Chyle, which is transferred through the whole Body, whereby the ſuperficial parts are diſcoloured.</p>
               <p>As to the biting of the Serpent, this yellowneſs is not eſſential from the poyſon of the Serpent, but from this Balſom that is ſent thither to antidote it, and ſo the Body becomes yellow: as I have inſtanced in a little Wormwood and Saffron.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</head>
                  <p>I have often cured it with a little Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merick roaſted in an Apple with a little Saffron.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe the middle Rind of a Barbary Tree, ſteeped in a little White-Wine, and a little Saffron, Flowers of Marygold, Rhubarb. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The yellowneſs of thoſe means ſhew their ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be for the ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Relique;<note place="margin">Vide Helmont:</note> for Signatures bewray the internal <hi>Craſis,</hi> or temperature of a thing; but the <hi>Craſis</hi> it ſelf doth not diſcover the thing.</p>
                  <p>Things of this nature have happily cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſeveral; but if thoſe ſhould chance to fail, my Powder doth it preſently.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:66140:76"/>
               <head>Calculus Veſicae: or the Stone in the Bladder.</head>
               <p>THe Stone in the Bladder (that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in nature) which well may be reckoned with thoſe Diſeaſes, that are the ſhame of Phyſicians. The cauſe and manner of its generation hath not rightly been underſtood by the Ancients: and our Modern Phyſicians having made no latter ſearch into it, there is yet no Remedy found out for the Cure, but the poor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable creature is left to the tyranny of this Monſter, or delivered up unto the tortorous way of cutting, which is ſuch a Remedy as was never inſtituted by God or nature.</p>
               <p>All men are liable to this Diſeaſe, though ſome more than others; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Children.</p>
               <p>You may obſerve, that in moſt Mens water there is this ſtonyfying matter, though it may not be diſcerned when it is hot and new; but after it hath ſtood ſome while expoſed to the cold, it is ſeparated
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:66140:76"/>
from the Urine, and remains in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Pot, or cleaves unto its ſides.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
                  <p>Men of ripe years are not ſo inclinable unto it as Children, becauſe they have a better digeſtion, and have not ſo much of that crude matter out of which it is made.</p>
                  <p>Old men are not incident unto it, though their Digeſtion be weak, becauſe they want quantity of the matter; but when the Ferment of the Bladder is weak in them, they are liable to the Strangury, which I ſhall ſpeak a word unto preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p>But Children are moſt inclinable unto it, becauſe they have weak Digeſtions, which breedeth abundance of Crudities, the Mother of this Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>It is more from the weakneſs of the Ferment of the Bladder where it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, than from the matter producing; neither is this matter coagulated and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened as Clay is by the heat of the Sun; but condenſed as Ice is, by the frigidity of the Air, And what inordinate heat is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:66140:77"/>
it is only accidental; as by that example before of a Thorn in the hand.</p>
                  <p>I could produce ſeveral inſtances to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate this truth; but I ſhall omit them at preſent.</p>
                  <p>The intention curative will ſhew it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Maxim; the trueſt Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is from the benefit or hurt of things formerly uſed: and that hot and warm things do mitigate and correct the pain, and cold things do exaſperate it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PROGNOST.</head>
                  <p>If it hath been of a long growth, and confirmed, I am ſorry to tell you, I know not what will diſſolve it. Such a Remedy hath been, if we will credit <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> which I believe to be true; and I hope God will diſcover it to ſome of us, for the comfort of thoſe miſerable creatures which are affected with it, and keep them from that torturing courſe of cutting, which very often proves a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>But when it is in doing, and of no long continuance, it may eaſily be prevented and reduced.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:66140:77"/>
                  <head>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</head>
                  <p>Now the Cure conſiſts principally in thoſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi> Evacuation, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration and Corroboration.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In evacuating the matter contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In altering the Ferment of the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if it be vicious, or</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In corroborating of it, if it be weak, which is commonly the cauſe.</p>
                  <p>And you can hardly evacuate the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before you corroborate the parts,; which is done by this courſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Victûs Ratio.</head>
                  <p>Let moſt of his Liquor that he drinks be Sack; let moſt of his Meat be roaſted well, whereof let him eat but little at a time, though he eat the oftener; let his Bread be Bisket, or the Cruſt of Bread well baked; let him eat Salt with his Meat; Salt Beef boiled is good for him, if he loves it, and doth well digeſt with him.</p>
                  <p>Let him avoid Milk, Cheeſe, let little Butter ſerve him, and fruits: an Apple
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:66140:78"/>
he may eat if he deſires it, Raiſins of the Sun he may freely eat.</p>
                  <p>You muſt foment or bath the Region of his Bladder often with Decoctions of ſome comfortable herb boiled in Sack, and ſome good Ointment to embrocate it afterward, and ſo bound up warm.</p>
                  <p>After ten or twelve days that you have kept the Child in this order, you may give him a Doſe of my Powder, which will bring forth the matter contained.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall direct any one further that ſhall deſire it.</p>
                  <p>But above all things, let him avoid all old womens Medicines to void or break the Stone; for I verily believe that hath made many a Stone where there would be none; for if the Bladder be any way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, whereby he doth not make water freely, they conclude preſently the Stone; and then take ſuch a thing, ſays one, and ſuch a thing, ſays another; and ſo keep giving till it come to a Stone indeed; for all thoſe things they give to force the Stone away, or break it, are inimical to the Bladder, and the more debilitates the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the efficient cauſe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating the Stone.</p>
                  <p>I dare affirm it poſſible to generate a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:66140:78"/>
Stone in any Body, though never ſo free from it, only by thoſe things they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly give to cure it.</p>
                  <p>I have been ſomewhat larger in this than I intended.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall only name two or three Diſeaſes more, and conclude; for I intend it only for a ſmall thing to carry in a man's hand for a <hi>Memorandum.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Enchyridion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So potent an Enemy is this Diſeaſe of the Stone to mankind, that it is very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom vanquiſhed or cured, except ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the affrightful way of cutting, under which many alſo die, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which recover, loſe the uſe and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Bladder for ever; ſome there are again who generate the Stone afreſh, after cutting, as <hi>Helmont</hi> notes, a young man who was twice cut, but the Stone growing again, the third time he died under the Knife. For indeed the cutting takes not away the power of making, although it may free a man from the matter made. Many Remedies have been invented to diſſolve the Stone; but experience hath found them but feeble helpers. Firſt, thoſe which have promiſed help by being
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:66140:79"/>
injected into the Bladder by a Syringe, as juice of Citrons, Spirit of Salt and others, becauſe they have been obſerved to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve a Stone in a Glaſs, taken from a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body; but alas their promiſes are vain, for a ſmall quantity being caſt into the Bladder immediately ſtirs up an intollerable Strangury, as being wholly foreign to the ferment of the part: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the powers of all common Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies taken at the mouth are altered, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted, and periſh before they get to the Bladder, for they muſt firſt paſs three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, ſo that little more than their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements can arrive at the Bladder; for acid or ſharp things, from whence ſo much hath been hoped, as ſoon as they are paſt the Stomach, loſe their acidity, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a ſaline nature, whereby the ſharpneſs is either wholly tranſmuted, or at leaſt ſo ſealed up, that it is devoid of an acid act before it gets to the Bladder. 'Tis true there are ſome things (as <hi>Turpentine, Aſparagus, Raddiſhes,</hi> &amp;c.) which have their odours ſo faſt tied to the middle life of their Concretes, that they are not wholly overcome by the Ferment of the Stomach, but retain them even to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling of the Urine, but thoſe are too
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:66140:79"/>
eeble reſolvers; and beſides perſevere not long in that eſtate, but quickly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to any dungy Ferment of putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Therefore a true Reſolver of the Stone ought to have the following powers and properties, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It muſt have a ſufficient power to diſſolve the Stone, being put with it into a Glaſs in a heat not exceeding the heat of our Bodies; and that not after the manner of Corroſives, which make a forcible diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution with an ebullition and noiſe, but by the action are much weakened in their own force: but a true ſolvent acteth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noiſe or ebullition, diſſolving the Stone inſenſibly, as warm water diſſolveth Ice, neither is its own power infringed, or depauperated by the action.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Solvent of the Stone ought to be ſo homogenious and ſingular, that it ſubmit not to any digeſtions or fermental powers through which it paſſeth in its way to the Bladder, that coming thither in its own integrity and might, it may work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stone as oft as it paſſeth by it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It ought to be ſo amicable and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Bladder, that being caſt into it with a Syringe, it may not be painful there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to after the manner of ſharp injections.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66140:80"/>
Such a Remedy I have a near proſpect of, but no more of that in this place: but I have a Medicine that will give eaſe in the moſt racking pains of the Stone, within the ſpace of an hour.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Atrophia or Maraſmuss: or, a Conſumption without a Cough.</head>
               <p>A Conſumption without a Cough pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the loſs of the Ferment of ſome principal part, whereby it decayeth and withereth, and ſome other part doth too much abound and increaſe: I ſhall ſpeak a word of this in the Rickets of Children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:66140:80"/>
               <head>Febris Hectica: or, a Conſumption with a Cough.</head>
               <p>A Conſumption with a Cough of ehe Lungs, is from the decaying and putrefying of them, either in part, or in the whole, nature ſending a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary proportion of nouriſhment to that part, which by that putrefactive Ferment is converted into Excrement, and is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorated, or coughed up.</p>
               <p>This Diſeaſe hath been ſeldom cured, if it hath been long on the party, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his Body is much emaciated and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paracelſus</hi> had a Remedy for it: but I think it was buried with him:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Riverius cent.</hi> 4. of obſerv. by the fumy <hi>Troch Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigm.</hi>
                  </note> others have cured it likewiſe, after a great loſs of their Subſtance.</p>
               <p>Whilſt it is in <hi>fieri,</hi> or in the beginning, I am very confident this <hi>Arcanum,</hi> or Powder of mine will cure it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:66140:81"/>This Diſeaſe is uſually the conſequent of a Surfeit or Fever, or elſe it is Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, being tranſmitted by the Parents to their poſterity, which admits of no cure, that I know of by Medicine: the former may be cured, if good Medicines be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in time, that is before the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and Lungs be too much vitiated, and the Lungs exulcerated. But it is in vain at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by the uſual Methods of Sugared Milk, nouriſhing Broths, Jellies, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hochs, Electuaries, pectoral Syrups, and Apozems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for they all add to the heap of Excrements, Milk and Broth of Fleſh being ſubject to putrefie ſpeedily by the very heat of the Stomach, not meeting with the digeſtive Ferment thereof (which is almoſt loſt) ſubmit to a vitious Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and ſo form a vile and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Chyle, which is in no wiſe fit for the nouriſhment of the Body, whence all the parts languiſh and waſte; the which alſo enrageth the <hi>Archeus,</hi> from whence that burning in all the ſolid parts proceeds, the which is evidently proved by being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, always an hour or two after eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Then as for Electuaries, Lohochs, Powders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some of them are deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to relieve the Lungs, by ſliding down
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:66140:81"/>
the Wind-Pipe inſenſibly, and ſo going immediately to the part affected, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are appointed to go about, till by the Laws of Circulation they may at length come with their aſſiſtance to the Lungs, but both to no purpoſe: as for the firſt nature derideth the offer, in as much as ſhe plainly ſheweth an abhorrency but of the leaſt crum or drop that through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inadvertency paſſeth the Larynx, and gets into the Wind-pipe, and will not be at reſt till by coughing it be driven back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: therefore who ſees not that if thoſe licking Medicines ſhould go that way their appointers would have them, that inſtead of curing or eaſing a Cough, how migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily they would increaſe it.</p>
               <p>As for the latter, they are forced to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the fate of the Food, only they prove more troubleſome to the Body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe more crude. But the cure of this Diſeaſe ought to be inſtituted after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner, <hi>viz.</hi> by cleanſing away of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lth, and altering the putrefactive Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent of the Lungs, the firſt makes room for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n equal diſtribution of the nouriſhable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ices: and the ſecond reſtrains the exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itant Governour of the Lungs from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erting their proper nutriment into pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:66140:82"/>
excrements. But when I ſpeak of cleanſing away of Filth, I do not mean ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by direct purges, or by thoſe things called Expectoraters: for the firſt are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed poyſons, and reſolve the good juice themſelves, and expel them with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, and the latter promote cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption faſter than they cauſe ſpitting But true cleanſers reſolve all filth in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, Guts and Veins, and in their paſſage carry them to the common Emunctories of nature, as thoſe of the firſt paſſage to be expelled by ſtool, and they of the Veins by Urine. To which purpoſe you may take <hi>Tartarum Vitriolatum</hi> every morning for three or four days together, from ten to twenty grains in a little warm Broth, increaſing the doſe every morning, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof for thoſe who affect no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſharp things, you may give half a dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or two ſcruples of the <hi>Cream of Tarta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> diſſolved in hot Broth: after which gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Salt of Harts-horn and Amber,</hi> of each eight, nine, or ten grains twice a day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Broth, or Sherry Wine, continue it fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome time, theſe will cleanſe away Filt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Excrements, as Soap cleanſeth Clot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and likewiſe reſiſt putrefaction; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the farther pacifying the <hi>Archeus</hi> of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:66140:82"/>
Lungs, thoſe who have <hi>Mineral Sulphurs</hi> well prepared, or <hi>Opium</hi> diveſted of its Narcotick or Stupefactive Power (which ſleepifying force is not its virtue, but its vice) ſuch I ſay may be able to cure this Diſeaſe ſafely and pleaſantly. But ſeeing thoſe Remedies are known but to few, therefore after (the forementioned Salt) I adviſe the <hi>Balſam of Sulphur of Antimony, or good Balſom of common Sulphur,</hi> to be taken twice or thrice a day to ſix or ſeven drops, or more at a time mixed with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle white Sugar, and taken upon the point of a Knife. But the <hi>Arcanum</hi> and Balſamick Pill do not miſs the cure, if nature be not too far ſpent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Rickets.</head>
               <p>THe Rickets is a Diſeaſe amongſt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that hath been but of late years: but ingenious <hi>Coke</hi> tells us, it hath been known among the Ancients, who have excellently treated of them: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:66140:83"/>
have the Learned Doctors <hi>Glyſſon</hi> and <hi>Bates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Culpepper.</hi> They differ but little, and conclude, that it is moſtly from an obſtruction either in the Liver or Spleen.</p>
               <p>I rather think it to be from a debilitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or viciouſneſs of their Ferment, and ſo there is no aſſimilation, whereby the part becomes atrophied, or decayed, and ſome other part increaſed: for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of one part is the growing, or greatning of another part: as I have often obſerved.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Atrophia,</hi> or Conſumption, and this, are Couſin-Germans, there is little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between them. Children do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound more with a crude phlegmatick matter, which makes the Head bigger, and the Joynts knotty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>PROGNOST.</head>
                  <p>If they have continued long, they are not to be cured, but if taken in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, my <hi>Arcanum,</hi> or Powder doth cure it preſently, and two or three of my Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamical Pills to be taken after, to rectifie the Ferment; for the <hi>Arcanum</hi> opens the Obſtructions, and ſweeps off all the pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant matter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:66140:83"/>If the Childs Head begin to grow big, let it blood in both ears. I have known it very effectual, and ſometimes it hath made a perfect Cure, without the help of any other thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the Bark of Aſh and Tamarisk each three drams, to which add a ſcruple of Salt of Tartar, put them into a Glaſs Bottle, with a quart of good Beer, let it ſtand twenty four hours, and afterwards let the Child drink it for common drink.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When it is out, you may put to the Bark another quart of Beer, and it will be good. If you will make it pleaſanter, you may add to it two or three ounces of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of Harts-tongue.</hi> Continue the uſe for ſome conſiderable time. <hi>Ens Veneris</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo excellent, being given twice a day to three or four grains, or more, in warm Broth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:66140:84"/>
               <head>Apoplexy, Paraliſis, Catalepſie, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilepſie, Vertigo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are ſeveral Diſeaſes that have been thought to have their Riſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the Brain, as Apoplexy, Epilepſie, or Falling Sickneſs, Catalepſie, or the ſleepy Diſeaſe, Palſie, Giddineſs of the Head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but it is not my judgment that the Brain is primarily affected in any of them.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Apoplexy.</head>
                  <p>An Apoplexy proceeds from a vapour of ſome poiſonous matter that hath for ſome time lain either in the <hi>Pylorus,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Diaphragma,</hi> or Midriff, or <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pochondria,</hi> fermenting and corrupting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:66140:84"/>
                  <head>Vertigo.</head>
                  <p>It is not of ſo poiſonous and malignant a nature as the Apoplexy is; it is ſomewhat narcotical, or ſtupefactive, as Tobacco is to them thac cannot well take it. It is the Forerunner of an Apoplexy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PALSIE.</head>
               <p>AS Giddineſs is the Forerunner to an Apoplexy; ſo a Palſie is the Subſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, or Follower.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
                  <p>It is cauſed by the horrour or great fear (in the vital and animal ſpirit of the Brain) by thoſe terrible aſſaults that are given them by that dreadful Enemy the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy. As we may ſee ſometimes many perſons do tremble and ſhake for fear.</p>
                  <p>I know ſome Palſies have been occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:66140:85"/>
by hurts and colds in ſome great Joynts, as Shoulder and Hips, and in progreſs of time that whole ſide hath become paraly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. How vain hath been the receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed opinion of the Schools, about Palſies, that they ſhould proceed from Obſtructions in the Head, or Conjugation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Lethargy doth proceed from a more mild poiſon than the Apoplexy; as from <hi>Opium. Epilepſie,</hi> or Falling Sickneſs, I have ſpoken of before.</p>
                  <p>They all affect the Brain by conſent of the parts where the peccant matter lies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</head>
                  <p>All theſe (beſides the Palſie) are cured by my <hi>Arcanum univerſale,</hi> if ever they be cured at all; which is to be haſtened, for if not remedied in the beginning, hardly find any cure.</p>
                  <p>The Palſie is an accident, or product, or the effect, and this may remain, though the cauſe be removed, it is rather <hi>Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries</hi> than <hi>Morbus;</hi> an affrighted Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the Spirits, than a Diſeaſe; and the Cure may be performed by my Balſamical Pills, which do refocillate, comfort, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:66140:85"/>
cheriſh the ſpirit, as alſo by Salt of Pearls, or Corral, or my <hi>Aurum vitae,</hi> either of them taken alone, with a little ſharp Wine drank after doth excellently.</p>
                  <p>From a weakneſs and decaying, of the ſpirits, this may be occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">My ſpirit ſhall be diminiſhed, and my days ſhall be ſhorten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> as well as by terrour in them: therefore this is one of the Diſeaſes of old age. And to go about to cure it in old perſons, if it hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued any time, is to ſwim againſt the ſtream, and write in the Sand.</p>
                  <p>In the Apoplexy, the Ointment for the Head and Neck deſcribed in the Cure of the Falling Sickneſs is good; as alſo the following mixture, the mouth being firſt opened by art.</p>
                  <p>℞ <hi>Aqua Langii, Water of Sage and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender of each an ounce, Tincture of Caſtor half a dram, Spirit of Sal Armoniack a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Oil of Amber nine or ten drops, Syrup of Staechas an ounce, mix them, and give a ſpoonful very often.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Palſie, Vertigo, Catalepſie,</hi> &amp;c. are all of the eſſence of an Apoplexy, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer only in degree, therefore they are to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:66140:86"/>
be cured with the like Medicines. In the Palſie, Lethargy, and Swimming, or Gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs of the Head, thoſe following Pills are effectual.</p>
                  <p>℞ <hi>of Pill. Aloephangina a ſcruple, Roſin of Jallap ſix grains, Salt of Amber as much, Oil of Marjoram two drops, mix them, and make four Pills to be taken in the morning ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and repeated once in three or four duys.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Palſie ſweat betwixt purgings with ſpirit of <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> given in Sack. You may alſo uſe the Ointment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned to the Back-bone and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralytical parts.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>October</hi> 1667, a certain Man-ſervant to one of the Arts-Maſters of <hi>Bridewel, London,</hi> was ſuddenly ſtricken with a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe in the Evening, as he was at Supper, he fell from his ſeat ſenſleſs and ſpeechleſs, his eyes were ſtaring open, as in a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſie or Congelation, but totally depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both of ſence and motion, as in an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy. When I firſt ſaw him he had remained in this condition about a week, during which time means had been uſed to help him, but proved altogether inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, ſo that he was given over for dead. Notwithſtanding which, I obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he yet retained a good degree of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:66140:86"/>
heat, as alſo an indifferent Pulſe, the which with ſome other conſiderations made me to believe he might ſtill recover, the which I told his Maſter and Miſtreſs, when they demanded what I thought of his condition, who then deſired I would take him into my care, which I did. The firſt thing I gave him was a Doſe of the Powder, which wrought very well up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and downwards, towards the end of which he began to ſpeak ſome odd words, and came to be ſomewhat ſenſible; the next day I repeated the Powder which wrought again as before, upon which he came to perfect ſenſation, and alſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in ſpeech, and one ſide returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the exerciſe of all Functions, but the other remained paralytical and inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from Head to Foot, not being able ſo much as to ſtir one Finger on that hand; but by the uſe of the Balſamick Pill, and repeating the Powder once or twice more (by the bleſſing of the Almighty) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored him, and in a months time was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at work, uſing thoſe uſeleſs Fingers, without which he could have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, being a Glover by Trade.</p>
                  <p>In the time that I had this perſon in cure, the Wife of another of the Arts-maſters
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:66140:87"/>
in <hi>Bridewel,</hi> having lain in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed about a Fortnight, was alſo one Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuddenly deprived of her ſpeech, and taken ſomewhat Paralytical on one ſide, ſhe ſent to me about eleven or twelve of the clock that night; as ſoon as I came, I gave her four grains of the Powder, which wrought both upward and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but moſt upward, the which being once or twice repeated, and the Balſamick Pill for ſome time taken at nights, ſhe was alſo happily recovered. I could give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other notable inſtances of Cures of this nature performed by theſe Medicines, (having had many fallen under my care) but theſe I think may ſuffice.</p>
                  <p>However, I will in this place add ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrange Cure (which comes freſh in my mind) done with the Pill alone, by a Phyſician, who buys Medicines of me, and lives near <hi>Highworth</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi> At a certain time he being abroad about ſix miles from his dwelling, was much ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Friend to go a little out of the way to look upon a poor man that had lain bedrid for three months, being grievouſly pained all over his Body, and not able to turn himſelf, but as he was helped; he had uſed Purgations, Phlebotomy, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:66140:87"/>
Unctions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but all to no purpoſe. The Phyſician having ſome of the Balſamick Pill about him, diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a full Doſe in a Glaſs of Ale, and gave him, and ſo left him, within two or three days the poor man came that ſix miles on foot to give him thanks, and told him, that within two hours after he had taken the Pill, he was perfectly free from pain, and ſo remained, with the due uſe of all the parts, only weak; the Phyſician gave him another Doſe home with him, which he took, and became very well, and had been ſo many months when the Phyſician told me of it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Spaſmus: or, Convulſion.</head>
               <p>A Convulſion is cauſed by ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant matter contained in the Guts, as is oftentimes ſeen after the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſome Hellebore or <hi>Stibium,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Medicine that hath a poyſonous quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:66140:88"/>The Sting or biting of any venomous or poiſonous creature produceth Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
                  <p>That vital <hi>Blas</hi> or Spirit in the Muſcle being aſſaulted by ſome poyſonous quality, contracteth it, the better to defend it from that poyſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SPASM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</head>
                  <p>The Cramp is from a ſharp aiery <hi>Blas,</hi> that doth meet with a Nerve or Sinew.</p>
                  <p>The Worms in Children bringeth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions in them many times.</p>
                  <p>That it is cauſed through fulneſs or emptineſs, and the primary place affected to be the Brain, I do not conſent unto, though it hath been received for a truth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</head>
                  <p>If it be cauſed by ſome poyſonous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that hath been received, or through the biting or ſtinging of ſome Snake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> my <hi>Aurum vitae</hi> is admirable: but if it cometh by excrementitious matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:66140:88"/>
in the Body, as the matter of Worms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the <hi>Arcanum</hi> or Powder e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radicates it, or takes it away by the root. They are generated from corrupted Chyle, and they differ according to the place where they are made.</p>
                  <p>If in the Stomach little ſmall Worms.</p>
                  <p>In the Ilion long and ſlender like earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms.</p>
                  <p>In the Colon, little ſhort thick worms, much like the Bots in Horſes. This Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der doth not only take away Diſeaſes when they are on, but likewiſe prevent them, if it be given in health; for this violent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe in Children, I verily think there is not a better remedy under the Heaven, if it be timely given; for it carries off all that may be the occaſion of the Diſeaſe or Worms, one Grain is ſufficient, and that's but ſix pence.</p>
                  <p>The laſt are the worſt, and ſometimes the longeſt in curing.</p>
                  <p>If theſe continue long, they encompaſs themſelves into a <hi>Ciſtis</hi> or Bladder, which they run out and into, as a Coney into her Burrough, whereby they defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the injury of any thing that is ſent into the place to kill them.</p>
                  <p>For the two former the Powder cures
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:66140:89"/>
them perfectly, not only in killing, or bringing away the worms there made, but in taking away the cauſe.</p>
                  <p>The laſt, if they have made this ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is very hard to kill and deſtroy them.</p>
                  <p>I have known a young Gentlewoman that was troubled with them from ſeven years till ſhe was nineteen, and never could get remedy: they conſtantly came from her day and night, without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement, to her great grief and ſorrow, though the pain was not intolerable. Now becauſe I do deſire to be found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious to my Countrymen, I ſhall freely tell in what my two or three <hi>Arcanums,</hi> or ſecret Medicines will not avail them, and direct them unto that which will do it.</p>
                  <p>Many Phyſicians were befooled in this Diſeaſe of this Gentlewoman, ſhe took the advice of all within that Country where ſhe lived: many were the Clyſters that ſhe took of ſalt, ſharp, and bitter things, with the like ointment, and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to her Belly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but all to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; as well as abundance of Mercurial Preparations which ſhe took.</p>
                  <p>She was cured by this following.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Worm dried (which is the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:66140:89"/>
beſt thing to deſtroy them that is) and powdered and given in a Clyſter with Milk and a little Honey.</p>
                  <p>But firſt let the Belly be well anointed and chafed with this Ointment.</p>
                  <p>Take ſome of the ſame Powder of the Worms, the Gaul of an Ox, a little Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar and Bay Salt, three or four Cloves of Garlick, the juice of Worwood,<note place="margin">You may have it at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries.</note> and the Powder of <hi>Coloquintida;</hi> if you have not the art to bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Ointment with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, beat the Garlick, and mix them, and ſo rub the Region of the great Gut, and dip a Cloth in it, and lay to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, do it warm.</p>
                  <p>In the Month of <hi>December,</hi> 1677, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing extreme cold Weather, great Froſt and Snow, a young Woman being with Child, and living near me, laboured un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a very ſtrange Convulſion, joined with a Palſie; for beſides the Fits which were ſtrange and long, ſhe had continually night and day, in Bed, and out of Bed, inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Convulſive Motions throughout her whole Body, for ſhe had not the command of any part, neither could ſhe ever ſit or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:66140:90"/>
lie ſtill, without drawing and writhing her Legs, Arms, and whole Body after a ſtrange exorbitant manner; ſometimes ſhe could ſpeak a little, and ſometimes nothing for many hours: but that which was moſt ſtrange was this, that when ſhe had ſome liberty of ſpeech, and would endeavour to relate her own apprehenſions of her evil, her Tongue would be all on a ſudden retracted, or drawn back into her Throat, that ſhe could never proceed, ſo that moſt people that ſaw her thought her to be bewitched, or under an evil Tongue, as they commonly phraſe it, but (by the mercy of Almighty God) I perfectly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her with this Powder and Pill, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ten days time; ſhe went out her time with Child, which Child and her ſelf have been ever ſince in good health. She had been almoſt as bad the year before, and was cured then by a Phyſician of <hi>Hartford,</hi> who buys Medicines of me. Before every Fit ſhe could manifeſtly perceive her great diſturber to ariſe from about the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and Midriff, and aſcend to her Head, which is a plain demonſtration that the primary Seat of this Diſeaſe is not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Head as is commonly believed, the whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alſo is not a little confirmed by thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:66140:90"/>
Children who are ſuddenly cut off by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, whoſe Bellies I have ſeen imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after death to turn yellow, green, or black, and cold before the extreme parts, which plainly indicates the ſeat of this putrefactive deadly Ferment, to be the Stomach, or thin Guts.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt theſe Diſeaſes, I ſhall inſert a Diſaſter, (though out of its place) and give my judgment thereupon, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eruptio Venarum: or, the Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Vein.</head>
               <p>THe Breaking of Veins in any place, are not without ſome danger. The place where the eruption is, ought princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to be known; for unleſs that be rightly underſtood in vain doth any one think to do any good, as to a Cure.</p>
               <p>The Schools have left it very obſcure to their Scholars, becauſe it was never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. by them; for indeed it doth
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:66140:91"/>
come meerly under the conſideration of an experienced Chyrurgion: to lay a plaiſter to the Heel for a hurt in the Head, is like to do but little good.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I ſhall give you ſome ſigns, that you may know the place, and ſome directions for its Cure.</p>
               <p>If it be below the <hi>Diaphragma,</hi> or Midriff, this Blood is evacuated moſtly by Urine. If in the Meſaraick Veins (which are annexed to the Guts) by Stool.</p>
               <p>If from the upper Region of the <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax,</hi> or Breaſt, it muſt come through a Thruſt of ſome ſharp Inſtrument that hath penetrated the <hi>Pleura,</hi> or inner skin of the Ribs; for without that there cannot be any Blood come into the Breaſt; for the Lungs or Heart, which are the two principal parts contained, cannot be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any Blows, Strains, Bruiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without this <hi>Pleura</hi> be pierced or broken: and beſides, there are no Veins in them, they are nouriſhed by Arteries; the Lungs by the <hi>Arterialis,</hi> which doth beſtow many ſmall Twigs into its Body, whereby the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are nouriſhed.</p>
               <p>There hath been many great miſtakes a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout this part in this Diſaſter; for a Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> having been broken in the Intercoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:66140:91"/>
Muſcles, or Muſcles of the Sides or Breaſt, Blood many times is evacuated at the Mouth; and likewiſe in the Head or Throat, Blood falling down upon the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyglottis,</hi> or Lap that covers the Wind-Pipe, cauſeth a tickling, which doth ſtir up a Cough, with which this Blood is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuated out of the Mouth, and thereby the Throat and Tonſils, and Glandules, or ſpungy places which do receive the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity of the Brain, are inflamed. Alſo the Spittle may become more craſs or fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; and being diſcoloured by the Blood falling there, many have preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it to have come from the Lungs.</p>
               <p>Without it were a Vein in the Head, the party himſelf may very well tell where the eruption is; for he can as perfectly perceive it to flow, as if he ſaw it. But in the Head he cannot, for he only finds a diſtilling and tickling in his Throat, with ſome pain in his Head. If this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling be from the <hi>Dura,</hi> or <hi>Pia Mater,</hi> it is very dangerous, if from ſome branch about the Throat, not ſo dangerous, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be the Jugular, which pours out ſo violently, without any intermiſſion, that in few hours life will expire.</p>
               <p>If it be in thoſe Panicles, <hi>Dura,</hi> or <hi>Pia Mater,</hi> which cover the Brain, the pain of his Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:66140:92"/>And eſpecially that ſide where the hurt was, will increaſe, and likewiſe his Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>The Cure doth ſolely conſiſt in open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Skull, and that place where he feels his pain moſt, to ſtop and cleanſe away the congealed Blood.</p>
               <p>If it be in the Throat, in applying ſtrong Defenſitives round the Throat, and next repellers to the Head and Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, opening a Vein in the Foot, and ſtrong Ligatures or Boundages to his Thighs, a little above his Knees, with vulnary and ſpecifical means.</p>
               <p>If it ſhould be in the containing parts of the breaſt, as in the Muſcles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> letting blood, with diſcuſſive means to the place, giving him ſome proper thing to ſtir up a gentle ſweat, cures him.</p>
               <p>But if there ſhould be a Laceration, or renting of the <hi>Pleura,</hi> with an Eruption of a Vein in the ſides, (which is a thing hardly ever heard of) whereby the Blood doth fall into the concavity of the Breaſt, the Cure is thus:</p>
               <p>Make inciſion upon, or as near the place as you can, where the Eruption is, then to tie the mouth of the Veſſel is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of ſome, but I would rather reſtrain
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:66140:92"/>
the Blood by ſome fit means, whereof my Powder for Wounds is admirable, uſed as in the Directions; and ſo it is for <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhagia,</hi> or bleeding at the Noſe, a Tent of Tow or Lint, and armed with the Powder, ſtays it preſently; or any where elſe, if it doth but touch the mouth of the Veſſel, immediately ſtops the blood. Remove it not preſently, but let it unite and heal the Veſſel firſt, which it will not be long in effecting.</p>
               <p>But if there ſhould be any Blood fallen down upon the <hi>Diaphragma,</hi> or Midriff, which ſhould not be preſently evacuated, but there lies coagulating, (which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by ſome weight in the place, and likewiſe a Fever to aſſault him, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant increaſe;) In that caſe, if the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice where you cut to ſtop the Vein, may be ſo high, whereby you cannot make it depending enough for the evacuating this blood, there muſt be another Orifice made more lower for that purpoſe. But this operation doth belong to an experienced Chyrurgion.</p>
               <p>Thoſe internal Wounds are very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and a great deal of circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be had about them; and are not to be cured but by a skilful Chyrurgion,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:66140:93"/>
that is well acquainted with thoſe opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are the higheſt practiſe in the Art.</p>
               <p>Wherefore have a care you are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with any old Wifes Stories of <hi>Tom Thumb,</hi> and <hi>Jack</hi> of <hi>Newberry,</hi> &amp;c. to tell you of a Vein broken in the Lungs, or Heart, or Liver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ('tis juſt as they tell you about Diſeaſes) 'tis a great ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity to ſpeak it; and ſhould an Artiſt ſpeak it, he would be laughed at by thoſe that underſtood the nature of ſuch things: for, the two Roots of Veins in the Liver, either of them hurt, death preſently enſues.</p>
               <p>If it ſhould be asked, what Veins ſhould be broken in the Lungs and Heart, whether the <hi>Vena Arterioſa,</hi> or the <hi>Arteria Venoſa?</hi> There is not any Vein in the Lungs: only ſome ſmall Twigs of the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>terialis,</hi> or Artery, which are diſperſed through them, by which they are nouriſhed: and for what uſe are the Ribs, but to defend them from ſuch injuries? and it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they ſhould be hurt by ſuch accidents.</p>
               <p>And in caſe what they ſay were granted to be true, there is no other way under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſave his life, but immediately to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that operation of a <hi>Paracentyſis,</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:66140:93"/>
which is, to make an orifice in the ſame ſide, whereof there is no more danger in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming, (by him that hath done it, and knows what belongs to it) then in opening a Vein in the Arm, though probably there may be ſome profeſſors of Art, that what they never ſaw, neither underſtand, they ſpeak againſt, and tell of danger in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Air, and letting out ſpirits, and a great many more nonſenſical Stories.</p>
               <p>Pray be adviſed, that you take but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle notice of it: for although they may be old practitioners, yet look on them but as young Artiſts.</p>
               <p>Fluxes of Blood, without ſudden help will ſoon flux out life; and to expect a Cure from thoſe that know not a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor the place where to apply it, ſeems very ſtrange to me.</p>
               <p>And beſides, without it be well cured in the beginning, it will break out again upon certain times, which at laſt will kill him; whereof I have known many ſuch examples. Wherefore get the beſt advice you can from Chyrurgions. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be from the Head, (as I have before told you) the party can very well tell you himſelf where the hurt is; for he will not only perceive the Blood to flow, but he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:66140:94"/>
will find ſome pain there: if it be from the Head, he will perceive a great dulneſs and heavineſs, and pain in his Head, with a tickling, as it flows down into his Throat, ſometimes ready to choak him, which ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth up a Cough, whereby this Blood is caſt forth from the Amygdales, or Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules, which are of each ſide the Wind-pipe, and thoſe ſpungy places about the Throat; and ſo ſome have thought them to be from the Lungs, when alas 'tis from the Head.</p>
               <p>I did preſage this in a Gentleman of this Town. Mr. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> only by his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Relation (which he can well tell) of his pain, which was in the fore part of his Head: I adviſed him, by all means, immediately to be let blood, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, if occaſion ſerved; for I told him,<note place="margin">Which that night happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him, and he died in the morning.</note> if he did bleed at the mouth, before he was let blood, he would preſently die, for he would be beyond all means, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he was ancient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the place diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to apply the Trepan, or Trefine, without which, I look on it as impoſſible <hi>(quoad artes)</hi> for any to recover, unleſs the blood be diſcharged, which falleth
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:66140:94"/>
between the Skull and the Panicles, which cannot be done by any other way.</p>
               <p>For what happens in the lower Belly, it is to be cured as wounds, by vulnary Drinks and Clyſters.</p>
               <p>I have been a little longer on this than I intended; but thoſe internal wounds are of high concernment, and I fear not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood by all pretenders to Art.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Coryza, Catarrbus, Tuſſis, Aſthma.</head>
               <p>COughs and Catarrhs, Rheums in the Head, Eyes, Noſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> proceed from the Evening cold, ſharp wind beating upon the † ſpungy Bone of the Head.<note place="margin">Ethmoides os cribriformae.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſthma,</hi> or ſhortneſs of Breath, cometh through a vicious matter contained in the Wind-pipe, or Lungs. I have not time to inlarge upon them.</p>
               <p>The three firſt are commonly cured in one night, by one of my Balſamical Pills.</p>
               <p>The laſt by the <hi>Arcanum.</hi> I have ſtrong
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:66140:95"/>
reaſon from experience to believe, there is not another ſuch Medicine found for it in any place that ever I was in: this is a Diſeaſe that old age is liable unto; and for old perſons that have had it long, 'tis folly for them to think to receive a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Cure from it, or from any thing elſe, but I know not any thing will eaſe them more than this.</p>
               <p>There is another Diſeaſe that follows old age, which I ſhall likewiſe hint at, and ſo end, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Stranguria: or, the Strangury.</head>
               <p>THe Strangury is from the defect and weakneſs of nature in the ſecond Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</head>
                  <p>Let him forbear all ſharp meats and drinks, and obſerve the ſame courſe I have directed for the Stone, in which he will find great comfort.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:66140:95"/>For any Venereal Diſtemper, or <hi>French</hi> Diſeaſe, there is not a better Medicine that ever was prepared for it, than this <hi>Arcanum;</hi> for it cures any, of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſoever (that is curable) without Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livation or Fluxing.</p>
                  <p>There are ſome Diſtempers belonging to the Female Sex, that are not here ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to expreſs, for which this <hi>Arcanum</hi> is ſingular.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hyſtericus: or, Fits of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</head>
               <p>IN Hyſterical Fits, or Fits of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there hath been a great miſtake, as to the true cauſe, a well as of the reſt. With one doſe of my <hi>Arcanum univerſale,</hi> and one of my Balſamical Pills: I have cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome in twenty four hours.</p>
               <p>The Seeds of <hi>White Nettles</hi> bruiſed, and drank in White Wine are a very good remedy againſt theſe Fits. So is alſo
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:66140:96"/>
the <hi>Tincture of Caſtor, Spirit of Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack,</hi> and <hi>Elixir Proprietatis,</hi> being given in Rheniſh Wine. But I have a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine which I call <hi>Elixir Hyſtericum,</hi> with Which I never yet failed to cure thoſe Fits.</p>
               <p>I have alſo that Remedy mentioned by Mr. <hi>Couch</hi> for the ſpeedy delivering Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with Child.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe in barrenneſs, in all the Authors that ever I read, I never met but with one that ever came near the Buſh; and it is very unlike that any of thoſe ſhould ſtart the Hare.</p>
               <p>I am confident there are many that are married who are childleſs, that ſhould they be divorced, the Husband would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Children by another Woman, and his Wife conceive by another man.</p>
               <p>Now if one ſhould demand the reaſon why could they not procreate when they were together. I doubt it would puzzle an old Phyſician to reſolve it.</p>
               <p>It may be he might tell them of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies in their Natures: as the Stomach doth abhor ſome kind of Meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I ſuppoſe thoſe Meats had firſt injured the Stomach. It may be if the Mother love
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:66140:96"/>
not Cheeſe, ſhe may cry pah unto it, to her little Daughter, and thereby the Child may loath it as much as the Mother.</p>
               <p>But I never knew a <hi>Pica</hi> in the Mother to beget a <hi>Crapula</hi> in the Daughter, though ſhe may labour <hi>cum furore matricis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But no more of this.</p>
               <p>This Diſcourſe deſerves more to be whiſpered in a private Room, than to be treated of here.</p>
               <p>And no marvel that there are ſo many incurable Diſeaſes, in regard their true cauſes were never hitherto found out.</p>
               <p>Thus you may perceive what a Lethargy and blind ignorance hath benighted Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, &amp; obſcured the Inquiry into the right Remedies for Diſeaſes, by a ſad Theory, and miſerable method of the Heathens, (which is ſtill in force amongſt Chriſtians) as if Medicine was made only for them, and the true knowledge God ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover unto them, and Chriſtians were to receive it from them. And well may healing fail us, who make no further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after it, than the tradition of ſuch Teachers.</p>
               <p>I have ſome other <hi>Arcanums,</hi> or Secrets, for ſome Diſtempers of the Female Sex, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for Women in Travel, which
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:66140:97"/>
commonly delivers them in a very ſhort time; (I have known ſeveral within half an hour) after the taking of it; and without the tenth part of that pain which they would have without it.</p>
               <p>There are ſome weak or aged perſons that digeſt very badly, whereby they are troubled with crudities, lack of appetite, pains in the Head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> my <hi>Arcanum uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſale</hi> may be a little too quick for them; wherefore I make up a Pill, which I call my Stomach Pill. There is a Diſpenſato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry called by that name, which moſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries ſell; but alas, one Pill of mine is worth twenty of them for goodneſs, and whoſoever ſhall try them ſhall ſay ſo. I give but one at a time, and that is at night going to Bed, though you have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped freely before; in the morning it gives two or three Stools, without the leaſt gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or pain at all, it doth not only digeſt thoſe Crudities, and take away the pain of the Head, but it doth likewiſe ſtrengthen both the Head and the Stomach. I am confident whoſoever ſhall once try them will never take any other Pills.</p>
               <p>As I have recommended two principal Medicines for the curing of your Diſeaſes,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:66140:97"/>
which proceed from within, ſo I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend another unto you, for the healing the Wounds and Hurts from without.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen Cuts, or Hurts, or Bruiſes, that have been very inconſiderable in the beginning, which afterwards for want of ſome proper Remedies became matter of great moment and danger.</p>
               <p>Therefore to prevent the like, I will accommodate you with ſuch a Remedy as the world doth not yield a better. It is of far more worth than all the Balſoms Oyls, Oyntments and Plaiſters that ever was yet made for that intent.</p>
               <p>There hath been a great talk about the weapon-Salve, and Sympathetical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; they are not worthy to be her Chamber-maids.</p>
               <p>Any wound, if it can, but reach the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om of it, it cures at the firſt dreſſing, and within half an hour after you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppli'd it, it takes away the pain and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>welling, and draws out any Thorn or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>plinter got into it, let it lie on, till it be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eady to come off of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>I verily believe it will cure an ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, (that is, a Leg or Arm cut off) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one dreſſing, you need not fear, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Bone appear, there ſhall not be any
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:66140:98"/>
exfoliation nor diſcolouration, which I have well experienced ſeveral times.</p>
               <p>I want words to praiſe it to its merit; only this I ſhall tell you, that whoſoever ſhall uſe it, will bleſs God for it, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire it with me.</p>
               <p>As for an Ulcer it is not proper, becauſe a Wound and an Ulcer are of different Natures, and this is ſpecifical to a wound, or Laceration, or Rending, or tearing the fleſh and skin.</p>
               <p>But whoſoever ſhall deſire it for an Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, I ſhall but change an Ingredient or two and make it as effectual in any cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ulcer, as in a Wound, but then you muſt not expect to have ſo ſpeedy a cure a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in a wound.</p>
               <p>I have recommended three or four <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canums,</hi> or ſecret Medicines unto you; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proteſt unto you, I would rather loſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowledge of all things in the diſpenſato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry than the worſt of thoſe.</p>
               <p>And as they are the beſt Medicines, they are the cheapeſt.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Arcanum univerſale</hi> or Powder, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doſe or quantity taken at a time, is fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> half a grain to ſix, which is the higheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I will ſell it for ſix pence a grain.</p>
               <p>My balſamical Pill, twelve pence: whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:66140:98"/>
is as well worth it, as any ſix Pills in the diſpenſatory are worth ſix pence.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Aurum vitae</hi> two pence a grain.</p>
               <p>As for my ſpecifical Powder for Wounds, Bruiſes and Hurts, you ſhall have enough for your money: you ſhall have an ounce for five ſhillings, which may be enough to cure a dozen ordinary hurts or wounds; How it is to be uſed I ſhall direct you.</p>
               <p>I have omitted to ſpeak of ſeveral diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes this <hi>Arcanum</hi> or Powder is a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for, I am very confident, there is not any diſeaſe that any Country doth infect men withal, but it is a ſingular Remedy for.</p>
               <p>Laſt year I had a Patient that went to <hi>Virginia,</hi> And he took a Doſe of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der here, and carried a Doſe of it with him; but he proved very healthy himſelf, and gave it to one that was Sick of that Country Diſeaſe, and it preſently cured him.</p>
               <p>If any Maſter of a Veſſel, that carries not a Chirurgeon with him, pleaſe to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome of this Powder in caſe of Sickneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſome of my Balſom for Cuts or Wounds; I engage, if once he carries it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith him he will not go without it at any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, if he can get it. And what he doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake uſe of, I will take again, and return
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:66140:99"/>
him his mony as he paid me for it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are many ready to ſpeak evil of what they know not, and ſome whoſe judgment may be defiled through preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, may ſay, that this is more to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit my ſelf than you, and that you may not be deceived. I declare, that whoſoever ſhall uſe any of theſe things according to direction, and if he do not find me faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in my relation, and himſelf bettered by it, the loſs ſhall not be his, but mine, I will return him his mony again.</p>
               <p>Accept it with ſuch an affection as it is proffered, or the good it brings may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the God of health make it ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful, for from him comes healing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Unto whom give all the Glory.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:66140:99"/>
            <head>Courteous READER</head>
            <p>LEt thoſe great Intervals that I had whilſt I was writing this ſmall Tract plead my excuſe; for not digeſting it into a more Methodical way of treating of Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>You have every thing as then I thought on it. I muſt confeſs it is <hi>hic &amp; ubique.</hi> Occaſions did then follow me that I was ſo far from having time to new write it and ſet it in order, that I hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly took a ſuperficial view of it. If thou think the Meat good, reject it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not ſo neatly Cook'd, nor preſented to the Table in its due and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Seaſon. I minded not <hi>Oratio,</hi> but <hi>Ratio,</hi> for I think it Eloquent enough, ſo it be underſtood by thoſe I princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:66140:100"/>
intend it for: wherefore thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt excuſe me, and do not carp at words, but take thy Pen, and correct with me, which is no more than I would do for thee upon the like occaſion. <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:66140:100"/>
            <head>I thought to have ſevered the Directions how to take the Powder, from the Book, but I am adviſed to annex it; which I have done.</head>
            <head>Directions.</head>
            <p>YOu may take the Powder in any thing, or without any thing: I commonly give it in the pap of an Apple, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, or a little bit of Bread, to the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Pill, it matters not what it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without either taſte or ſmell, ſo that the moſt nauſeous Stomach may freely take it. It will not diſſolve in any Liquor, therefore you may leave ſome of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, if you give it in any Liquor: I have
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:66140:101"/>
given it in a little beer in a ſpoon, to Children that would not take any thing elſe, then be ſure to give it all. Its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are various, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the matter offending, and the place where it reſides; that way which nature thinks moſt convenient for her, for the diſcharging that matter which ſhe is willing to be rid of.</p>
            <p>Sometimes by Stool, by Urine, by Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and ſometimes by Sweat, I have known it work effectually, and yet by neither of thoſe ways, but by breaking wind upward and downwards, as I have ſhewed in the cure of the Fiſherman, for it draws wind out of any part of the body effectually. If the matter be in the Stomach, which commonly it is in Fevers, &amp;c. then it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten works by Vomit and Stool: If the matter be more in the Guts, it works by Stool alone. In Dropſies, and ſuch Diſeaſes as water doth abound, it works by Vomit and Urine. What of ſuch aqueous matter is contained in the parts containing, it drives forth by Sweat plentifully.</p>
            <p>The time; in Winter, and when the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is cold, I give it in the morning, with a benefit of a fire in the room, but in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer I give it at night: but let them not
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:66140:101"/>
eat any ſolid meat that day, but if the party be very ſick, never ſtand upon any time, whether day or night give it him; the ſooner the better: but it is beſt when the Stomach is empty from meat.</p>
            <p>It commonly works about half an hour after, take nothing before it works of it ſelf, and then if you pleaſe to drink a little warm poſſet drink, or beer, you may. And if it ſhould work by Vomit more then you would have it, take a little thin Gruel or Broth, ſo ſeaſoned with Salt that it taſteth well of it; and that makes it work down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but I have given it to Children and others that never took any thing in the working of it; for what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it hath wrought upon, it will bring away, whether you take any thing or not.</p>
            <p>If you are diſpoſed to ſleep, you may freely do it, without the leaſt prejudice unto you, for nothing can hinder the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, nor the bringing it away.</p>
            <p>I never knew it fail to work in my life (where it hath been retained in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach) But in caſe it ſhould not, you need not fear; it will do you no more hurt, then if you had taken ſo much Nutmeg, or Cinnamon, and if you pleaſe you may
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:66140:102"/>
take a glaſs of Sack, or a dram of the Bottle, without any dammage at all.</p>
            <p>As for my ſpecifical Powder for wounds, or hurts, of that nature, take the white of an Egg and beat it well, then take ſo much of it as may well wet a pledget, and ſo much lint ſcraped from an old rag, or ſo much tow as will cover the hurt, then mix ſo much Powder with the white of the Egg, as you think will make it to the conſiſtence of honey, ſtir them well together, and the lint, or fine flax, or tow in it, and lay it to the place, bind it on very gently, only ſo hard as will keep it from falling off. And although it doth preſently cure it, yet you had not beſt take it off in fourty eight hours, I never knew it fail. And in caſe it ſhould not be perfectly well, you may take a little more, but it is not one Hurt or Cut in a thouſand that you will uſe it twice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be a deep thruſt, or ſhot in the Thigh, where it may not reach the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, but for any ordinary hurt though it be never ſo broad, or torn, it cures it at the firſt dreſſing, and takes away all pain and ſwelling in half an hour, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſtops the bleeding; Remember, the ſooner you apply it the better.</p>
            <p>But if you are at Sea, where the white
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:66140:102"/>
of an Egg is not to be had; then take the powder and caſt it upon the hurt or wound, and take a fine linnen cloth or ragg, dip it in ſalt water, and then wring out the water well, and lay the cloth ſeveral times double upon the place hurt, and bind it on gently (as before) and it will prove as effectual as the other way.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall deſire it for an Ulcer, I ſhall ſo make it, that it ſhall cure any cureable Ulcer, in a very ſhort time.</p>
            <p>This is to be kept in ſome dry place, or carried about one; for againſt moiſt and rainy weather, it will be a little moiſt, wherefore keep it near the fire, and if it ſhould be moiſt at any time, dry it at the fire, and it will be as good as at the firſt.</p>
            <p>It will not decay, you may keep all the Powder twenty years, and be as good as at firſt. The Stomachical Pills you may keep ſeven years.</p>
            <p>I am fully perſwaded, and I have reaſon to think, that there is not any Diſeaſe (either in the <hi>Weſt</hi> or <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> nor any where in the World, but this Powder will take off. I ſhould not queſtion to cure the Plague, with my <hi>Arcanum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſale,</hi> and my <hi>Aurum Vitae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any Practitioner ſhall deſire any of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:66140:103"/>
thoſe <hi>Arcanums,</hi> I ſhall accommodate him with them upon reaſonable terms, I will engage, that any Chyrurgion that hath once found the worth of them, he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have one Dragme, than a Cheſt of ten pounds worth of the laudableſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thartical Medicines he can chuſe.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Pillula Balſamica,</hi> or Balſamick Pill, is to ſettle the Body, and to reſtore it into a good temper, (for a Houſe that hath been fired; though the fire be out, yet there may be a great heat and ſmoke) which I give the next Night after my Powder. If you take the Powder in the Morning, take the Pill at Night, if there be occaſion; that is, if he find his Body much diſordered, or out of temper, or feels any pain, then it is good to take one of thoſe Pills, otherwiſe not. If you pleaſe you may drink after it: In the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer give after it a Glaſs of White Wine, Cider, or Ale; in the Winter a draught of warm Poſſet-Drink, or warm Ale, or a Glaſs of Sack.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Aurum Vitae,</hi> is when the Malignity of the Diſeaſe hath tainted the Spirits; and that is known by this, though the Cauſe be gone, and the Effect removed, yet the Party doth not become well, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:66140:103"/>
in a lingring condition, then give him a Doſe of this in the Morning in his Bed, let him drink it in a glaſs of Sack, or warm Poſſet-Drink, and it will drive it out by ſweating, and let him continue ſweating for three or four hours, never fear it, it will not weaken, but make ſtronger.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Pill. Stomachica,</hi> or Stomack Pill, is to be taken at Night, as any other Pill, without taking any thing after it.</p>
            <p>Thus I have directed you as plain as I could: And a good ſucceſs ſhall be ever prayed for unto that God that alone can give it, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend <hi>R. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:104"/>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:66140:104"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe Doſe of the Balſamick Pill for one of full years is twelve, four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, or fifteen grains, yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times twenty, in robuſt bodies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream pains; a Child new born may take a grain of it diſſolved in breaſt milk, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A Child of my own being born with the gripes, began to take it the next day, it was likely to die all the Moneth, and very weakly for the firſt quarter; ſo that if the Pill were omitted but one Night, it were even at deaths door, ſo that the uſe thereof was continued with happy ſucceſs till it was a year and a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter old, for the Teeth ſake: at which time it was weaned from the Breaſt and Pill both together, without the leaſt inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency, or alteration when it left it, and bleſſed be God, of a poor weakly Child, became luſty, ſtrong, and forward, as any
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:66140:105"/>
Child of its Age whatſoever, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains being now in its third year of Age.</p>
            <p>The Powder for Old Sores or Ulcers mentioned by Mr. <hi>Couch,</hi> I alſo prepare and ſell by the name of <hi>Species Phagadeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> at the ſame price with that for wounds and blood-ſtopping, and is to be uſed thus. Take a full pint or better of fair water, ſet it over the fire in an Earthen Pipkin till it be ſcalding hot, then put in an ounce of this Powder by degrees, ſtirring it with a wooden <hi>Spatula,</hi> then cover the pipkin and let it ſtand half a quarter of an hour, over the fire without boyling, then take it off, and let it ſtand till the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be clear, the which keep in a Glaſs or Earthen bottle; when you uſe it to any Old Ulcer or <hi>Fiſtula,</hi> put a little into an Earthen Sawcer, warm it as hot as it may be endured, then waſh the Sore by dipping a fine rag in it, and at length double the rag three or four times, and let it be well wet with the warm Liquor, and apply it to the Sore; if the Ulcer be hollow or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulous, ſo that you cannot come at it to waſh it, then inject the Liquor warm with a Syringe; let it be dreſſed twice a day, and I dare aſſure you that there is no cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Ulcer whatſoever that this will not
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:66140:105"/>
cure; if you deſire to have the water yet ſtronger, in ſtead of fair water infuſe the Powder in Lime-water. This water is not only a Cure for Old Sores, but for Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms, Tetters, Mangineſs, Itch, Scabs, and ſuch like Curaneous Diſtempers, they being waſhed therewith, and linnen clothes wet therein laid upon the place. The way of uſing the Powder or Balſom for Wounds and Blood-ſtopping is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught by Mr. <hi>Couch;</hi> that I call by the name of <hi>Species Vidneraria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doſe of the <hi>Aurum Vitae</hi> for one of full years is ten or twelve grains, and ſometimes more, it may be taken in a little Sack, Ale, or Poſſet drink, or made into a <hi>Rolus,</hi> with a little Conſerve of Roſes, or any Cordial Syrup; it may as well be taken at Night going to Bed, as in the Morning, provided the Patient hath eat but a light Supper, and that two or three hours before.</p>
            <p>This is a powerful Remedy in any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant <hi>Fever, Small-Pox,</hi> or <hi>Meaſels, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, Scurvy, French-Pox, &amp;c.</hi> It mightily purifies the Blood, and refreſheth the Spirits.</p>
            <p>All thoſe Medicines mentioned in this Book may be had at my Houſe (except the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:66140:106"/>
Water mentioned for Embrocation in the Gout, which I know not) at the ſame prices that Mr. <hi>Couch</hi> ſold them; but Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Chyrurgions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall have them at my Catalogue price. I have alſo ſome other Medicaments of ſingular uſe and efficacy, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Oyly Volatile Salt of <hi>Sylvius de le Boe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Whoſe vertue and uſe is at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in his new <hi>Idea</hi> of Phyſick, the firſt Part, in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>This was ſome time ſince ſold in divers places in <hi>London,</hi> I mean ſomewhat having the ſame name ſtamped upon it, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this Famous <hi>Sylvian</hi> Medicine were to be found in it. I had it from a Gentleman who was divers years a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent under <hi>Sylvius,</hi> and was alſo Brother and Executor to <hi>De Graaf,</hi> from whom <hi>Sylvius</hi> would hide nothing, in whoſe Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy he found it after <hi>De Graaf</hi>'s Death Price 6 <hi>s. per</hi> ounce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Elixir Hyſtericum.</head>
               <p>This is an Excellent Remedy againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fits of the Mother, the which I never y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:66140:106"/>
knew it fail to help, it is alſo very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the <hi>Epilepſie, Convulſion, Vertigo, &amp;c.</hi> It is to be taken three times a day, the quantity of twelve, fourteen, or fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen drops at a time in a Glaſs of Sack, or Ale where Sack is not to be had, as alſo in the time, or rather upon the approach of any Fit, it may be taken to thirty or forty drops, for there is no danger of exceeding the Doſe. Price 5 <hi>s. per</hi> ounce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Manna Mercurii.</head>
               <p>This preparation of <hi>Mercury</hi> is ſo well diveſted of its Malignant Volatile Salt, that it never cauſeth Vomiting or Saliva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (as the beſt of the Common Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, eſpecially if they be ſometimes repeated) whereby, it is made ſo innocent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat it may be as ſafely introſumed as <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a.</hi> It is a great Specifick in the <hi>French <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ox, Leproſie, Scurvy,</hi> and <hi>Itch,</hi> againſt all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enereal Nocturnal Pains; as alſo Pocky <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lcers and Puſtules: it cauſeth the Scabs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſently to fall off, and diſpoſeth the Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers to heal. I aſſure you I have known a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontumacious Pox cured by this Medicine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one; and which is more, a Phyſician <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce told me that he had cured one with
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:66140:107"/>
three Doſes of it only, with the help of a little <hi>Bezoardicum Minerale,</hi> which he uſed ſome time in ſtead of a Sudorifick Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et drink, and which is a hundred times better. The Doſe is from ſix Grains to twenty made up into Pills with Roſin of Scammony or <hi>Extractum Rudii.</hi> The beſt way is to begin with a ſmall Doſe at firſt, and increaſe every time as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: If it ſhould work two or three days together (as it may do where it meets with a <hi>Plethora</hi> of ſordid Matter) there is no danger, but on the contrary the Cure will the ſooner ſucceed. Price 12 <hi>s. per</hi> ounce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Aqua Venerea.</head>
               <p>This Water or Liquor cures the moſt ſtubborn Venereal Ulcers or Sores in a few days time, they being waſhed with it twice a day, and rags three or four times double wetted in the ſame, and lay'd upon them Price 5 <hi>s. per</hi> pint.</p>
               <p>Moreover all Chymical Preparations i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſe may be had at my Houſe, a Catalog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of which with the prizes any may ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>gratis:</hi> Or any Perſon that deſires to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:66140:107"/>
any Curious Proceſs wrought, may be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved faithfully therein, by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>CHR. PACK.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From my Houſe at the Sign of the</hi> Globe <hi>and</hi> Chymical Furna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>in the</hi> Poſtern <hi>near</hi> Moor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, <date>1680.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:108"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books Printed for <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Harford</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>GEll</hi>'s Remains, being ſundry Pious, and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Notes and Obſervations on the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, opening and explaining it, wherein Jeſus Chriſt, as yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for ever, is Illuſtrated, by that Learned and Judicious man, Dr. <hi>R. Gell,</hi> late Rector of St. <hi>Mary Aldermary, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in two Vollums, <hi>Folio</hi> price 30 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtian Religion's Appeal from the Groundleſs Prejudice of the Scepticks to the Bar of Common Reaſon; Wherein is proved, 1. That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did not delude the World: 2. Nor were themſelves deluded. 3. Scripture Matters of Faith have the beſt Evidence. 4. The Divinity of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures is as Demonſtrable as the Being of a Deity, by <hi>John Smith</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Colcheſter, Folio</hi> price 12 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Admired Piece of Phyſiognomy and Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romancy, Metopoſcopy, the Symmetrical Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Signal Moles of the Body, fully explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with their Natural Predictive Significations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delightful and profitable, with the Subject of Dreams made plain; whereunto is added the Art of Memory, by <hi>Rich. Saunders,</hi> Illuſtrated with Cuts and Figures, <hi>Folio</hi> price bound 12 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The New World of Words, or a general Engliſh Dictionary, containing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Proper Significations, and Etymologies of all Words derived from other Languages, the Fourth Edition, containing beſides an Addition of ſeveral Thouſand Words, A brief View of the moſt Eminent Perſons of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents
<pb facs="tcp:66140:108"/>
in each Art or Science, Collected and Publiſhed by <hi>E. P. Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Longitude not found, or an Anſwer to a Treatiſe written by <hi>Henry Bond Senior,</hi> ſhewing a way to find the Longitude by the Magnetical incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natous Needle, wherein is proved that the Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is not, nor cannot be found by the Magnetical inclinatous Needle, by <hi>Peter Blackborrow,</hi> Gent. <hi>Quarto,</hi> price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Taxes and Contributions, very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for Stateſmen, <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Jeſuits Catechiſm according to St. <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> for the inſtructing and ſtrengthening of all thoſe which are weak in that Faith, wherein the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of their Principles, Perniciouſneſs of their Doctrines, and Iniquity of their Practices are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>Quarto,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De ſucco Pancreatico,</hi> or a Phyſical and Anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Treatiſe, of the Nature and Office of the Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creatick Juice, ſhewing its Generation in the Body, what Diſeaſes ariſe by its Viſitation, from whence in particular, by plain and familiar Examples, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatly demonſtrated the Cauſe and Cures of Agues, or Intermitting Fevers, hitherto ſo difficult and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, with ſundry other things worthy of Note, written by that Famous Phyſician, <hi>D. Reg. de Graaf</hi> of <hi>Delph,</hi> and Tranſlated by <hi>Chr. Pack Med. Lond.</hi> Illuſtrated with divers Copper Plates, <hi>Octavo,</hi> price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judiculus Univerſalis,</hi> or the Univerſe in Epitome; wherein the Names of almoſt all the Works of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of all Arts and Sciences, with their moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Terms, are in Engliſh, Latine, and French, methodically and diſtinctly digeſted, being of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular uſe to Perſons of all Ages, who are deſirous to attain to the Knowledge of the ſaid Tongues,
<pb facs="tcp:66140:109"/>
Compoſed at firſt in French and Latin, for the uſe of the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> by the Learned <hi>T. Pomey</hi> and now enlarged with the Addition of the Engliſh Language, and ſome other Supplements, by <hi>A. Love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> M. A. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Engliſh Military Diſcipline, or the way and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of exerciſing Horſe and Foot, according to the Practice of this Preſent Time, with a Treatiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all ſorts of Arms and Engines of War, of Fire works, Enſigns, and other Military Inſtrument both <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Modern, Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Count of <hi>Gabalis,</hi> or Conferences about ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cret Sciences; Bendered out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with an Advice to the Reader, by <hi>A. L.</hi> M. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Twelves,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Mathematical <hi>Compendium,</hi> or uſeful Practiſe in Arithmetick, Geometry, Aſtronomy, Geograph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Navigation, Embattelling and Quartering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Armies, Fortification and Gunnery, Gauging a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dialling, explaining the Logarithms with new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dices, <hi>Napar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Rods or Bones, making of Mov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, and application of Pendulums, with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Projection of the Sphere for an Univerſal Dial, <hi>&amp;</hi> Collected out of the Notes and Papers of Sir <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> More,</hi> by <hi>Nicholas Stephenſon,</hi> the Second Editio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with many Additions, <hi>Twelve.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66140:109"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
